<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A newe herball of Macer, translated out of Laten in to Englysshe</title>
            <title>Herbal.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1543</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03046</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13175.8C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103752</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839497</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839497</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3925</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03046)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3925)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 56:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A newe herball of Macer, translated out of Laten in to Englysshe</title>
                  <title>Herbal.</title>
                  <author>Macer, Floridus, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[120] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by me Robert Wyer, dwellynge in Saint Martyns paryshe, at the sygne of Saynt John̄ Euangelyst, besyde Charynge Crosse],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1543?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-P⁴.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 17173.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 17173 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>A version of STC 13175.1, published in 1525 with title: Here begynnyth a newe mater, the whiche is called an herball.</note>
                  <note>The attribution to Macer in this and in STC 13175.13c is false--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Botany, Medical --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Herbs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Materia medica --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3925:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3925:1"/>
            <p>¶A newe Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball of Macer.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in to Englyſſhe.</p>
            <figure/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="A" type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:2"/>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Gnus caſtus, is an herbe called Tutſayne or par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke leuys, and the leuys be ſom dele red, lyke to the leuys of orage, &amp; he hath a yelow flou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er aſmoche as a peny, &amp; beryth in the toppe blacke betye when they be rype, and yf they ben not type, they be yelow as the flower of the herbe, this herbe groweth moche in woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; drye places. ¶ The vertue of this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be is to kepe men &amp; women chaſte.<note place="margin">Chaſte</note> And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore as Diaſcoridon and Placent ſaythe it is colde, and called Agnus caſtus. Alſo this herbe openeth the poores, &amp; letteth out wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked humours and ſpyrites of a mannes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.<note place="margin">Body Mans ſeede.</note> This herbe diſtroyeth the moyſter of a mannes ſeede. Alſo the ſame auctours ſaith yf this herbe be ſoden with Fenell ſede and with a lytell ayſell,<note place="margin">Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye.</note> it wyll deſtroye the cold dropſye. Alſo yf it be ſoden with Smalache and Sawge in ſalte water, and then waſſhe the hynder parte of a mannes hed, it helyth &amp; vnbyndeth an euyll that is called lytarge.<note place="margin">Lytar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. Leche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> Alſo this herbe deſtroyeth the fowle luſt of lechery yf it be dronken, and men vſe to lye vpon hym or ſlepe vpon hym, and therfore ſomtyme men eate this herbe roſted, for yf
<pb facs="tcp:3925:2"/>
men eate it rawe, he wyll lyghtly engendre hedach.<note place="margin">hedach Mylt.</note> This herbe is good to deſtroy hard<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and ſtoppynge of the lyuer &amp; the mylte. Alſo a plaſter made of this herbe is good to do away the hed ache,<note place="margin">Hed humou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res.</note> that is ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred of wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked humours, this herbe is colde and drye, and there be .iii. ſpyces of her.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Smallache, or Marche.</head>
                  <p>APium is an herbe clepyd Smallache or Marche, This herbe hath leuys ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke to louage, but the leuys ben not ſo longe and it is not ſo ſtronge of ſauour as louage is, &amp; his ſede is lyke perſely ſede. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this herbe is to cauſe a man to make water.<note place="margin">make water. Lyuer.</note> And he openyth the ſtoppyng of the lyuer, Alſo the ſede hardnethe a mans wom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be and draweth away wycked humours of a mannes body to the hed and the ſtomacke &amp; the wombe,<note place="margin">wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be falling euyll.</note> and noyeth hym moch that hath the fallynge euyll, and women with childe, and other ſuckynge children, ſhulde not eate of this herbe for takyng of the fallyng euyll This herbe is hote and dry, and hath .v. ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of her.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Anetum.</head>
                  <p>ANetum is called Anyce, This herbe hath leuys lyke to Fenyll other dyll,
<pb facs="tcp:3925:3"/>
and the ſame ſauour, ſhe beryth ſede ſomde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le as the ſede of orage. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is to make a man to paſſe,<note place="margin">Rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blynge The yoſke. wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de yerde.</note> alſo this her be ſwageth the rumblynge of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be. Alſo he deſtroyeth the yoſke. And the ſee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of this herbe brent and ſtrawed on a wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de wyll hele it ſoone, and namely yf a man be ſcaldyd on his membres, or on his yarde, ſtrawe the powdre theron, &amp; it wyll hele ſoon Or what other maner euyll aryſeth in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes yerde. Alſo a playſter of the ſeede brent and layde to the Emerawdes hote heleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoone.<note place="margin">Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rawdes</note> This herbe is hote and drye. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Cherfoyle, Cheruyle.</head>
                  <p>APetium is an herbe clepyd Cherfoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, or Cheruyle. This herbe hath ſmal leuys lyke hemloke, but this herbe is ſwete in ſauour, and he hath a whyte flower &amp; a long ſede lyke otes. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is yf he be dronken he maketh a man to pyſſe well.<note place="margin">Ache. raynes wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> Alſo he delyuereth the ache in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes Raynes &amp; of the bledder. Alſo yf he be dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with wyne, he letteth out wicked wyndes from the ſydes, and ſtoppyng of the wombe and of the lyuer &amp; all maner wyndes. Alſo this herbe witholdeth caſtyng.<note place="margin">Caſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> Alſo a plaſter made of this herbe and temperyd with eyſel
<pb facs="tcp:3925:3"/>
diſtroyeth wylde fyre, and heleth the canker,<note place="margin">Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> and other woundes, and putteth awaye the chylle from all woundes. This herbe is one of the ſpyces of Smallache, &amp; he hote &amp; dry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶wormwode.</head>
                  <p>ABſynthium is an herbe called worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wod, and his leuys ben ſomdele why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, and he hathe a great moore, &amp; out of that moore come many braunches, and he flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth as dothe Mugworte. ¶The vertue of this herbe is to comforte the ſtomacke &amp; clen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> herte.<note place="margin">Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke Herte.</note> Galyen ſayth that this herbe hath two vertues, one is laxatyfe, the other coſty patyfe. And therfore he ſaythe that yf this herbe be gyuen for an euyll of the whiche the mater is not fully defyed, it ſhall harde the ſtomacke and let digeſtyon.<note place="margin">Dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. Lax.</note> And yf the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier of the euyl be ryped, than this herbe wyl make a man laxatyfe, and eaſely put awaye dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kenes. And yf this herbe be dronke with ſpykenarde it aſwageth the akynge of the ſtomacke and the wombe, that is gatheryd of wicked wyndes.<note place="margin">wides.</note> Alſo yf this herbe be tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peryd with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and dronken it heleth the ſwellynge in a mannes mouth,<note place="margin">Swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge. Iyen.</note> and putteth away the blackenes of a mannes iyen &amp; cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryth them moche. Alſo yf this herbe be ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb facs="tcp:3925:4"/>
with the galle of a Bulle, and after that put in to a mannes iyen, it dothe awaye all maner of ſhemeryng and dymnes of a man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes iyen.<note place="margin">Iyen. moy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter.</note> Alſo the iuce of this herbe ſtylled in to a mannes noſe thryle dryeth vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture that ronneth out of them. Alſo Diaſco rides ſayth yf this herbe be put in to a preſſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge clothes it ſaueth them from motthes Alſo yf it be layde amonge bookes wryten with ynke,<note place="margin">Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes. bookes</note> the wormes ſhall not eate them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Mugworte.</head>
                  <p>ARtemeſia is an herbe called mugwort This herbe is lyke to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuys of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mode, but they ben not althyng ſo rounde, and this herbe hathe a longe ſtalke, &amp; many ſtalkes comen out of the rote, and flowreth as doth wormwod. ¶ The vertue of this her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be is yf a man trauaylynge bere this herbe a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boute hym, he ſhulde nat be wery for his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle nor in his waye.<note place="margin">Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle. ſpirite. Ache.</note> Alſo where this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be is in any howſe, ther ſhall no wycked ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite abyde. Alſo this herbe ſtamped with ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe helyth the ſorenes and ache of mennes feete. Alſo this herbe made in powdre &amp; dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with blode warme water helyth the ache of a mannes guttes and many other,<note place="margin">guttes</note> and it is hote and drye. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:4"/>
                  <head>¶ Affodylle.</head>
                  <p>AFfodillus is an herbe called Affodyll This herbe hath leuys lyke to leekys and a yelowe flowere at the top, he hath rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de coddes, in the whiche is ſede lyke onyon ſede. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is the brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ben good to hele the dropſye.<note place="margin">Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye. Deno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Alſo the leuys &amp; the flowers dronken with wyne he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyth the bytyng of venomous beaſtes. Alſo the iuce of this herbe and the rote with a lytel Myrre &amp; a lytell ſaffron ſoden in olde ſwete wyne, &amp; than ſtrayned, is good to hele ron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng iyen.<note place="margin">ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning iyen. Heer grow</note> Alſo the rote of this herbe brent in powdre and put in to iyen that haue loſt theyr heer ſhall make heer to growe. Alſo &amp; a harde ſharpe clothe be wet in the iuce of this herbe and therwith anoynt with the cloth in the ſonne the Morfue and the bowe ſhal fall awaye, this herbe is hote and drye.<note place="margin">morfu.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Red Mader.</head>
                  <p>AStrologia lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ga, is called red Mader This herbe hath leuys lyke to mader, and he hath a braunche the length of a cuby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and many braunches co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of one rote, and the braunches haue many knottes ryght as mader, and hath a whyte flower. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is, that it wyl vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bynde 
<pb facs="tcp:3925:5"/>
the ſtoppyng of the lyuer,<note place="margin">Lyuer. wides. woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> and let out all wycked wyndes that ben ſtoppynge in a mannes body. Alſo this herbe clenſyth wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des that ben rotten. This herbe muſt be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theryd in harueſt and is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Galyngale.</head>
                  <p>AStrologia rotunda, is called Galyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gale, This herbe hathe leuys lyke to Burres, and hath but one braunche &amp; grene leuys aboue &amp; vnder ben whyte, and it flow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth as it were betayne ſaue the flowers ben whyte. ¶ The vertue as Ipocras ſayth yf he be dronke with hote water it is medycyna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble for men that ben ſtopped in the breſt and for fallynge euyll,<note place="margin">Breſt Euyll Cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe</note> and for the podagre and the crampe, and he muſt be gatheryd in Har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueſt he is a ſpyce of Mader, and he be hote and drye. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Sothernwode.</head>
                  <p>ABrotanum is an herbe named So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thernwode, This herbe hath a ſtalke lyke to Rue but he hath ſtreyghter leuys tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rue. ¶The vertue of this herbe is yf the fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be broken &amp; dronken with water it helyth men that haue ben bytten with venomous beſtes.<note place="margin">Veno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Alſo it diſtroyeth wormes in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes wombe.<note place="margin">wombe</note> Alſo the powder therof medled
<pb facs="tcp:3925:5"/>
with olde oyle and put to the place there lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth heer it ſhal growe agayne.<note place="margin">Heer</note> Alſo the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of this herbe breketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harde paſſion,<note place="margin">paſſion</note> this herbe is hote and dre.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Ameos.</head>
                  <p>AMeos is an herbe called Amee, this hath leues leke to Elderne, but they ben leſſe and a longe braunche and flowreth and ſedeth as it were perſely, and the ſedeis lyke to the ſede of Perſely. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is yf it be dronke with hony it ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wormes in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wombe,<note place="margin">wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> and vnbyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth great ſtoppynge of wycked wyndes in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wombe, he breketh the ſtone, he hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſtomacke yf it be colde,<note place="margin">Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke.</note> he clen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth the lyuer and the reynes and wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, he helpeth the bytynge of venymous beaſtes, and it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Allaluya.</head>
                  <p>ALleluya is a herbe called woodſore or ſtubworte, this herbe hath .iii. leues of the whiche .ii. ben rounde and a lytle depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aboue and it hath a whyte flower, but no longe ſtalke. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is yf it be roſted vpon the coles in leues of the red docke, then he ſhall frete awaye deed fleſhe,<note place="margin">deade fleſſhe.</note> and it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:6"/>
                  <head>¶Agrimonia.</head>
                  <p>AGrimonia is an herbe called Egrimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye, and the leues be lyke to Tanſey, but the leues of this ben greater, and he hath a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lewe flower, and when the flower is fall he hath fede that wyll hange in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, this groweth by dyches, or hedges, and wodes. ¶ The vertue is yf he be eten grene with the rote he heleth the akyng of the wom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be.<note place="margin">akyng wombe A ſore hurte mylte.</note> Alſo this herbe tempered with eyfell wyl heale a ſore hurted with yron. Alſo yf it be vſed in meates it wyll hele the ſorenes of the mylte, and it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Auancia.</head>
                  <p>AVancia is an herbe called Auendre, it hath leues lyke to an hare foote, this herbe is called harefote, and he hath a yelowe flower as it were Turmentyll. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue is yf he be dryed &amp; made in powder, and put in a lytel wyne or hote water and gyuen to a man that hath the Feuers to drynke,<note place="margin">the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers the can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker,</note> it ſhall helpe hym ſoone. Alſo it helpeth moche woundes, and the canker yf it be dronke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Altea.</head>
                  <p>ALtea is an herbe called the Holihocke or wylde malowe, it hath leues as it were malowe and hath a longe braunche, he
<pb facs="tcp:3925:6"/>
ſedeth as doth malowe. ¶ The vertue is yf it be ſhreded with talow,<note place="margin">Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre.</note> and taken to a man that hath the potagre, he ſhall be hole within thre daye. Alſo yf this herbe be ſoden with vynegre and with lynſede, and layde vnto a mans ſydes it departeth wecked gatheryng that ben gendred togyther in a mans body it groweth in feldes and hote places.<note place="margin">wycked gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Amariſta.</head>
                  <p>AMariſta is an herbe called Mawthen or docterfenel, this herbe is moch lyke to Camamyll, and flowreth as Camamyll, for it hath whyte flowers, &amp; this herbe ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth as it groweth in the felde, and in corne. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that the ioyce therof dronke is good for the canker.<note place="margin">the can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker. Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rawdes</note> Alſo to hele the pypes of the Emerawdes and there be two ſpyces of this herbe, one hath a whyte flower, the other a yelowe flower.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Aniſum</head>
                  <p>ANiſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is an herbe called Annies, it hath leues as Comen or Fenel, but the ſede is more than Fenell ſede.<note place="margin">wycked wides.</note> ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he vnbyndeth wycked wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and great humours, and he openeth the ſtoppynge of the leuer.<note place="margin">Lyuer.</note> Alſo he maketh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes mylke to wax. Alſo he ſtyrreth man
<pb facs="tcp:3925:7"/>
and woman to workes of kynde.<note place="margin">workes</note> Alſo it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a man to make water &amp; to ſwete. Alſo it maketh the wombe harde yf it be laxe, this herbe or elles the ſede ſhulde be take moyſte,<note place="margin">wombe</note> and roſted or perched in maner of medycyns this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Alleum</head>
                  <p>ALleu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is an herbe called Garlyke, this herbe is comen. ¶ The vertue of hym is that he wyll vnbynde all greate ſtoppyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and wycked wyndes in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes bodye.<note place="margin">wycked wi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des.</note> Alſo he helpeth a man to make water, but neuertheleſſe he greueth ama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes iyen for the great vnbynding and drawynge that he ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly draweth the ſyght. Alſo he dyſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a venym within a man. Alſo he healeth colde ſores as it were Tryacle.<note place="margin">venym within a man.</note> Alſo he dothe awaye the morfewe of bladders in what pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce that they ben of the bodye yf it be well rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed therwith, and it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Aſtraton.</head>
                  <p>AStarton is an herbe called Lunarye, this herbe groweth amonge ſtones or hye places, this herbe ſhyneth by nyght, this herbe hath his moyſture yfounde by ſhepher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in the felde, and it hath yelowe flowers hole and rownde as cokobell, or flowers of
<pb facs="tcp:3925:7"/>
Fogxloue, the leues of this herbe ben zende blewe, &amp; they haue the marke of the Moone in the myddes as it were .iii. leued graſſe, and the leues ben more then .iii. leued graſſe, and ben rownde as a peny, it hath a ſtalke &amp; that is red, it ſmelleth as it were Muſke, and the ioyce is yelowe, this groweth in the newe Moone without leues, &amp; euery day wareth a newe lyfe .xv. dayes, and after .xv. dayes he leſeth a lefe as the Moone wareth and way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and where ſoeuer this herbe be he gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in great quantite. ¶The vertue of this herbe is that who ſo eteth his bayns or els of the herbe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waynynge of the Moone when he is in ſigno verginis,<note place="margin">falling euyll.</note> yf he haue the fallyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge euyll he ſhall be hole. Alſo who ſo hath the fallyng euyll bere this herbe aboute his necke and he ſhalbe hole. And it hath many mo ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues than I can tell at this tyme.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="B" type="part">
               <head>¶The .ii. letter begynneth with. B.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Betonia.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Etonia is an herbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Betayne or byſchoppes worte, this herde hathe hole leues, but they be ende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by the ſydes without, &amp; it hath a
<pb facs="tcp:3925:8"/>
red flower in the croppe of the ſtalke. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is yf he be pune and put to the wounde in the heade that is ſmytten with a ſtroke,<note place="margin">wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in the hede</note> he ſhall hele the wounde fayre and well, and the better yf it be freſſhe. Alſo this herbe wyll drawe out broken bones of wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des as ſome Auctours ſayen. Alſo take the water of Betayne, or els breke the leues and take the ioyce and put it in to thyne iyes, than ſhall you fynde that it is good for akyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge or ſorenes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iyen. Alſo take of Betayn a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ragma and pune it and medle it with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that is warme,<note place="margin">broken bonesi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hede.</note> and drynke it .iiii. tymes faſtynge and it wyll breke the webbe aboute the iyen, and clenſe theym well &amp; fayre. Alſo yf thou haue waterynge iyen eate euery daye a lytel Betayne and it clenſeth them.<note place="margin">ſore iyen</note> Alſo if thou haue akynge iyen, take the leues of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne freſſhe by them ſelfe, or els with a lytel water, and then wrynge out the ioyce &amp; put therto a lytell roſe water, warme them well togyther, and ſtyll it in to thyne iyen, and af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terwarde put aboue wolle, and ſo thou ſhalte be hole. Alſo yf thou blede moche at the noſe take Betayne and pune it with a lytell ſalte,<note place="margin">Noſe blede.</note> and do it to thyne noſe thyrlles, as moche as thou mayeſt with thy thombe and thy medle
<pb facs="tcp:3925:8"/>
fynger,<note place="margin">blode.</note> and than holde thy noſethyrlle with the ſame fyngers, and the bloud ſhall ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Alſo yf thou haue ſore tethe,<note place="margin">ſore teth.</note> take Betayne and ſeth it in olde wyne, or in eyſell tyll it be ſodde to the thyrde parte, and holde it in thy mouth, and thou ſhalt amende.<note place="margin">The cowgh.</note> Alſo yf thou haue the cowghe take two ou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Betayne and a lytell hony, and ſeth it with eſy fyre, and vſe it .ix. dayes.<note place="margin">ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes yard be ſwolen</note> Alſo yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes yearde be ſwollen or els ſore, take Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne &amp; pune it with lytell wyne, and after laye to the yarde and he ſhalbe hole. Alſo yf a man may not holde his mete within hym, take .iiii. dragmes of the powder of Betayne and medle it with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny that is ſodde,<note place="margin">vome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge.</note> &amp; make pellettes as greate as a walſche nute, &amp; gyue hym .iiii. dayes eche day a pellet, and do hym to drynke .ii. ſponefull of that water, &amp; than he ſhall be hole. Alſo yf a man be potagre, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke Betayne and pune it &amp; lay it to his feete,<note place="margin">pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre.</note> and he ſhalbe ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. Alſo take a lytell Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne or the powder and eate it erely, and it ſhall helpe the fro dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes that day,<note place="margin">Dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes.</note> theſe medycynes ben proued, and hath many moo vertues. This herbe groweth in woodes and holly places amonge buſſhes in darke places, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:9"/>
                  <head>¶Balſaminta.</head>
                  <p>BAlſaminta is an herbe that men cal hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemynt, this herbe hath leues lyke vnto other myntes, and ſome men calleth it water mynt, it groweth moche by the water, but it hath a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger ſauer then hath another mynt. ¶ The vertue is that he wyll conforte the ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macke,<note place="margin">Purge mans ſtomak</note> &amp; make a man well to defy his meate Alſo this herbe purgeth a man within the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, and maketh hym well to ſpeke. Alſo the ioyce of this herbe medled with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and a lytell wyne doth awaye the ſchylke of amans ſtomacke, and other wycked wyndes of hym. Alſo the ioyce of this herbe dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke with wyne yſode maketh a woman with chylde eſely to bere her chylde,<note place="margin">wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with chylde.</note> &amp; ſoone to be delyuered, this is hote and drye, and hath two ſpyces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Beta.</head>
                  <p>BEta is an herbe called Bete, this herbe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men, and groweth in Gardaynes, and there be two ſpyces therof, and Diacoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſayeth, one is whyte another blacke,</p>
                  <p>¶ The vertue of this herbe is that the ioyce of this herbe putte it in to the noſethyrlles,<note place="margin">Heed ache.</note> it clenſeth a mans heed. Alſo this herbe ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the akynge of a mans heed. Alſo it clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the heed from nyttes,<note place="margin">nyttes</note> and from other ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men.
<pb facs="tcp:3925:9"/>
Alſo it repayreth &amp; kepeth the heer of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes heed.<note place="margin">Heer.</note> Alſo this herbe dyſtroyeth bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and byles. Alſo Diacolides ſayeth,<note place="margin">Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> that vpon the rote of this herbe maye be planted a graffe that wyll afterwarde beare fruyte, as vpon the cole rote.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Borago Domeſtices.</head>
                  <p>BOrago Domeſtices is an herbe called Borage, this groweth in Gardaynes, and he hath ſhorte leues and a blewe flower. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyl clenſe the red colour of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">colour Mery.</note> Alſo this herbe medled with wyne maketh a man glade and mery, &amp; it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Bigula.</head>
                  <p>BIgula is an herbe called Brome Bugle this hath leues ſomwhat rounde, and ſomwhat tournynge to blacke, and he hath a blew flower and ſomwhat boyſtous. ¶The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll hele woun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des in a mans heed.<note place="margin">woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hede</note> Alſo it breketh and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth the rewme in amans heade and the akynge, he groweth in woodes, and he is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and drye, and there ben .ii. ſpyces of hym.<note place="margin">reume.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Burneta.</head>
                  <p>BVrneta is an herbe called Burnet, &amp; it hath ablewe flower as hath Hayhoue, and leues lyke to Tanſey, but they be not ſo
<pb facs="tcp:3925:10"/>
great. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll diſtroy the great humours and the laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue within a man.<note place="margin">Laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue.</note> Alſo he healeth and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſtoppynge of the lyuer, and maketh a man to pyſſe. Alſo he healeth a man of the yelow euyll.<note place="margin">Lyuer.</note> Alſo the ioyce medled with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and dronke, vnbyndeth &amp; healeth the ſore of the rybbes and pappes, and there be .ii. ſpyces of this herbe one groweth in harde lande and hath lytell leues,<note place="margin">Sore rybbes.</note> another groweth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> medowes and haue more leues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Burſa paſtoris.</head>
                  <p>BVrſa paſtoris is an herbe called ſhepar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des purs or tocheworte, this hath leues departed ſomdele as Burnete, &amp; hath a why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te flower, and when he hath loſt his flower, he hath the maner of a purs, in the whiche is ſede ¶ THE vertue of this herbe is he wyll ſone ſtaunche blode yf he be dronke,<note place="margin">Forble<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge.</note> it groweth in feldes and gardaynes well nyghe all aboute, and he is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="C" type="part">
               <head>¶The .iii. letter begynneth with. C.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Camamilla.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Amamilla is an herbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Camamyll, this herbe hath leues lyke to the mauth &amp; whyte flowers but he ſmelleth ſote, and
<pb facs="tcp:3925:10"/>
the mawth ſtynketh.<note place="margin">For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone</note> ¶ The vertue is yf he be dronke with wyne he breketh the ſtone. Alſo he ſtroyeth the yelowe euyll. Alſo be healeth the akynge of the lyuer.<note place="margin">Euyll. Lyuer.</note> Alſo yf he be chowed he healeth the ſore of the mouth, this is hote &amp; drye, and groweth moſte in gardaynes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Calamintum.</head>
                  <p>CAlamintum is an herbe that is called Calamynt. this herbe hath leues lyke vn to Mynt, but the leues ben whyter and rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then the leues of Mynt, and more ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſauour, and it hath a whyte ſtalke.</p>
                  <p>¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye a manes talent as ypocras ſayth, and there be thre ſpyces of this herbe, one that is ſtonye, another y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is hery, another that is wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terye, and they be hote &amp; drye, and he that is hery maketh a man moyſte, he that is ſtony yf he be dronke he maketh a man that hath dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke venym hole.<note place="margin">for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nym</note> Alſo this herbe made in play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and layde to any venymous ſore, it dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the venym from within outwarde. Alſo who ſo drynketh this herbe .iii. dayes, it heleth the yelow euyl,<note place="margin">Euyll.</note> he that is herye it helpeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſepour, the ioyce of this herbe put in to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes eares, it kylleth the wormes therin,<note place="margin">eares. ſtomac</note> it comforteth the ſtomacke and helpeth to defye
<pb facs="tcp:3925:11"/>
and it withdraweth caſtynge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Craſſula maior.</head>
                  <p>CRaſſula maior, is an herbe called Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyn or Ormale, this herbe hath ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what thycke leues as it were Peny worte. ¶The vertue of this herbe is yf it be layde to a wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d he ſhall hele it without any helpe,<note place="margin">Sore wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds</note> this herbe groweth in gardaynes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Craſſula minor.</head>
                  <p>CRaſſula minor is an herbe called Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor or Stonecrope, it hath lytell leues lyke to Orpyn, and it groweth vpon howſes and walles and groweth ſomwhat hangyng. ¶The vertue of this herbe is,<note place="margin">For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ague.</note> he wyll make a man to lyue chaſte, &amp; is dronke for the ague.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Cituca.</head>
                  <p>CItuca is an herbe called Hembloke or herbe Benet, it hath leues lyke to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely, and ſo he flowreth &amp; ſedeth as doth Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely, but this herbe ſtynketh. ¶The vertue is he kepeth may dens pappes from great wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge.<note place="margin">Leche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre.</note> Alſo yf the ioyce of this herbe be dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke he diſtroyeth the great appetite of lechery. Alſo the ioyce of this with the ſpume of ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and ſwynes grece diſtroyeth the hote po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagre, and ſwageth the ſwellyng, this herbe is colde and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:11"/>
                  <head>¶Centuaria maior.</head>
                  <p>CEntuaria maior is an herbe that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth the more centory or earth gell, this hath leues lyke to the leſſe ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tory, but they be more whyter, and hath a ſtalke and yelowe flo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wers, and flowreth not but in the tope. The vertue of this herbe is yf it be ſodden with good wyne &amp; gyuen a man to drynke,<note place="margin">For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuer</note> it hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the ſyckenes of the lyuer. Alſo this herbe ſodden in wyne and dronke, dryeth vp wylde humours of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes mylt,<note place="margin">Mylt.</note> this hath ben ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proued. Alſo the ioyce of this herbe ſodden in water is good to heale a wounde of another place that is ſmytten with a canker yf he be a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noynted therwith, it is hote and drye,<note place="margin">Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kers.</note> &amp; gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in drye grounde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Centuaria minor.</head>
                  <p>CEntuaria minor is an herbe called the leſſe Centory or criſtus lader, this hath leues lyke to the more Centory, but the leues ben more grener, and he hath thre braunches co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge out of the more, &amp; the flower ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what rede. ¶The vertue is yf the powder or the ioyce be medled with olde wyne &amp; dronke is good to hele the ſtyngynge of an adder,<note place="margin">venym</note> or any other venymous beeſt. Alſo yf you haue ſore iyen,<note place="margin">iyen.</note> take the ioyce &amp; anoynte your iyen
<pb facs="tcp:3925:12"/>
and thou ſhalt be hole. Alſo yf thou haue any venym within the,<note place="margin">venym</note> take and pune this herbe &amp; tempre it with Ayſell and drynke it and you ſhall caſt vp all the venym, and it groweth in drye places.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Carin.</head>
                  <p>CArin is an herbe called caraway, it hath leues lyke ſomwhat to Fenell, &amp; a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſtalke and rounde ſede, more then the ſede of perſely. ¶The vertue of hym is that he dyſtroyeth wycked wyndes,<note place="margin">For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coughe</note> and the coughe, and heleth men that hath the frenſy, and by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng with venymous beeſtes. Alſo this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be medled with ayſell heleth ſcabbes &amp; tetters,<note place="margin">ſcabes</note> and reſtoreth heer where it falleth away, this herbe is hote &amp; drye,<note place="margin">Heer.</note> &amp; groweth in gardayns.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Celodonia.</head>
                  <p>CElodonia is an herbe called Celondin or Detenwort, this hath leues that ben grene and yelowe flowers, &amp; when he is broke he droppeth mylke, and the leues be ſomwhat lyke to Columbyne. ¶The vertue of this her be as Plinius ſayth, yf a ſwallowes byrde be hurte the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me fetcheth of this herbe &amp; healeth hym agayn.<note place="margin">Toeth ache</note> Alſo it healeth the ache of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tethe. Alſo it clnſeth a mans hede. Alſo it healeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> canker &amp; other ſores in the mouth,<note place="margin">kanker.</note> this is hote and drye.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3925:12"/>CIdamu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is an herbe called Herinote, or Dylnote, or Flete, or Haleworte, this hath leues lyke to Fenell, and whyte flowers and ſmall ſtalkes, &amp; groweth in woodes and medowes.<note place="margin">Deade fleſhe.</note> ¶The vertue is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll fetche awaye deade fleſhe. Alſo this herbe put on a ſore, or on a place that lacked heer, it heleth it and reſtoreth heer, this is hote and drye.<note place="margin">Heer.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Caulis.</head>
                  <p>CAulis is an herbe called Coleworte, this herbe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men to you. ¶The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of hym is that he wyll clenſe freſhe wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and the canker,<note place="margin">For ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re iyen</note> &amp; hele ſore iyen that haue almoſte loſt theyr ſyght. Alſo it maketh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans mylke to waxe, and he comforteth the ſtomake.<note place="margin">ſtomac Lepre.</note> Alſo the ioyce of this herbe tempred with alym &amp; eyſell ſwageth the lepre. Alſo it is good for dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kenes, &amp; groweth in gardayns</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Coriandrum.</head>
                  <p>COriandrum is an herbe called Cetrian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he hath leues lyke to erthenote ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dele, &amp; hath alytell white flower &amp; rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſede ſomwhate whyte, and he is ſtronger in ſauour.<note place="margin">wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body</note> ¶The vertue is yf the ioyce be dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with honnye, it ſleeth all the wormes in a mannes body, &amp; alſo hardeth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be. Alſo yf the ſede of this herbe be eate it driueth
<pb facs="tcp:3925:13"/>
away the Feuers that come the thyrde daye,<note place="margin">feuers.</note> this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Capillus veneris.</head>
                  <p>CApillus veneris is called mayden heer or water wortes, this hath leues lyke to Ferne, but the leues hen ſmall, &amp; gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vpon ſtones and walles, &amp; in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the leues is as it were a blacke heer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone venym.</note>¶The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the ſtone. Alſo yf it be dronke with wyne it dyſtroyeth the venym, he is colde and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Crocus.</head>
                  <p>CRocus is an herbe called Saffron, this hath lytell leues as it were graſſe, and blewe flowers.<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> ¶The vertue of hym is that he wyll dyſtroy all maner of abhomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the ſtomake.<note place="margin">To ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlepe</note> Alſo he maketh a man to ſlepe. Alſo the flower is good for many medycyns, and namely for cokes to coloure theyr potage and it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Centinodium.</head>
                  <p>CEntinodium is an herbe called Centi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodi or ſwyngraſſe, this herbe groweth welnye ouer all.<note place="margin">For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone</note> ¶The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll breke the ſtone, this herbe is hote &amp; dry, &amp; may be gathered at all tymes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Caprifolium.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3925:13"/>CAprifolium is an herbe called woodbyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de or withwynde, this groweth in hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or in woodes, and it wyll beclype a tre in her growynge, as doth ynye, and hath whyte flowers. ¶The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll hele cankers and woundes,<note place="margin">canker. Teth.</note> and bladers, and akynge of the teth, and ſores in a mans toes. Alſo it is good to hele ſwellynge that is ſmyten or ſtonge with been,<note place="margin">ſweli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</note> this is ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Canabaria.</head>
                  <p>CAnabaria is an herbe called wylde hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, and this hathe leues lyke to hempe. ¶The vertue of this herbe is that he is good for the Feuer, and groweth moche by water:<note place="margin">Feuer.</note> or moyſte grounde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Coſtus.</head>
                  <p>GOſtus is an herbe called Coſte, or leſſe dytayn, this hath leues as dytayn, but they be not ſo moche, and the leues be more whyter then the leues of dytayn. Alſo it is ſote in ſauoure. ¶The vertue of this herbe is that he helyth the ſekenes of the breſte &amp; of the long and alſo he wyll breke the Poſtym.<note place="margin">y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breſt. longes</note> Alſo he drawyth the humours of mans eyen. Alſo he is good for the ſtomake &amp; it is hote &amp; drye.<note place="margin">poſtim</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Cepe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3925:14"/>CEpe is an herbe called an Onyon this is comyn ynoughe. ¶The vertue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is that he wyll greatlye comforte the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make.<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> Alſo he neſſhyth the wombe. Alſo this herbe with honye and eyſell &amp; dronke is good to hele the bytyng of a hounde.<note place="margin">hound.</note> Alſo this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be medled with womans mylke heleth the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of earyn.<note place="margin">earyn.</note> Alſo the Iuce of this dronke with any lycure is good for a man that hath loſte ſodenly his ſpeche.<note place="margin">Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. reume.</note> Alſo the Iuſe put to a mans noſtrell breketh oute the reume or any other wycked ſtoppyng this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Columbina.</head>
                  <p>COlumbina is an herbe called Colu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>byne or culuerfote, this herbe is ſomedelle ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke Celydoyne, but he droppeth no myl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. ¶The vertue of this herbe is that he is good for a man that hath the Quincy and he ſhuld be gathered in Auguſt.<note place="margin">Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minum.</head>
                  <p>COminum is an herbe called Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn, this hath leues lyke to Coriander &amp; he hath many brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng oute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtoke and hath ſtronge ſauour.<note place="margin">wycked winde.</note> ¶The vertue is that he diſtroyeth wycked wyndes &amp; other euyll of the ſtomake. Alſo he healpeth a man to make water this herbe is hote and drye.<note place="margin">water.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:14"/>
                  <head>¶Cardiaca.</head>
                  <p>CArdiaca is an herbe called Cardiake or cylſper, this herbe hath leues ſomdele lyke to blynde nettell and he is pryckyd ſome dele vpon the tongue, and he hath lytell cod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and therin his ſede is.<note place="margin">Falli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g euyll.</note> ¶The vertue is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is good for men that haue the fallyng euyl. Alſo he is good for ſauces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Cicera.</head>
                  <p>CIcera is an herbe called frenſhe Peſche hath leues lyke another Peſe and alſo coddes, he hath not ſo great leues nother ſo longe coddes as hath the other peſe, and there be .ii. ſpyces of her white &amp; rede, &amp; he groweth in gardayns &amp; her ſede in ſhape as other peſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Camelion.</head>
                  <p>CAmelion is an herbe called wolueſciftyl or a white thyſtyll this herbe hath white leues great and brode kene and rede flower &amp; groweth in wayes. ¶The vertu of this herbe is great that yf thou take this herbe whyle the ſonne is in capricorne with the newe mone yf thou bere it with the or vppon the,<note place="margin">good.</note> there ſhall no myſchyfe come on the.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Conſolida maior.</head>
                  <p>COnſolida maior is an herbe called co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry this hath leues lyke to horſhele, but
<pb facs="tcp:3925:15"/>
they be not ſo whyte &amp; groweth in watry pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and there be .ii. ſpyes of her the one hath a white flower, the other a rede and lyke they be of one vertue. ¶ The vertue is, yf a man be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> burſyd within hym or broke take the rote of this herbe and roſte hym well amonge aſkyn and take hym to the ſeke faſtynge with hony &amp; let hym eate it,<note place="margin">For bruſyd.</note> and he ſhall be hole. Alſo this herbe hath broken leues and he is hote &amp; moy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte and he bereth blake ſede.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Conſolida minor.</head>
                  <p>COnſolida minor is called Dayſye or bruſeworte and he hath leues lyke to the leſſe Centory and a whyte flower. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is that he is good to breke botches yf he be punyd and layde therto,<note place="margin">Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> this is a ſpyce of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fery and he groweth well nye ouer all aboute in many dyuers places.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Conſolida media.</head>
                  <p>COnſolida media is called white Gotho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or white guldes this herbe hath leues ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dele enlouge &amp; they be endentyd a lytell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out and hath a whyte flower that is ſomedele lyke to dayſe and it groweth in medowes and lees, and hath dyuers vertues.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="D" type="part">
               <head>¶The .iiii. letter begynneth with. D.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Dragancia.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3925:15"/>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ragancia is an herbe called Dra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gance, or Elderworte or cerpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne, this herbe hath .iii. leues in eche brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che &amp; they be ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dele ſhar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe as a neddyr. ¶ The vertue is &amp; he be punyd with wyne he putteth away all venym.<note place="margin">venym</note> Alſo he helyth akyng of eres and they be anoynted therwith. Alſo yf the powder of this herbe be blowen in a mans noſe it cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyth the noſe from connyng.<note place="margin">Eres.</note> Alſo it is good to dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroy the Goute and the canker &amp; the feſteri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of woundes.<note place="margin">Goute</note> This herbe groweth in wodes &amp; hylles,<note place="margin">canker.</note> and he is hote &amp; moyſte in the moneth of Iune and Iuly he muſt be gathered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Diptanum.</head>
                  <p>DIptanum is called Dyteyne, or ditan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this herbe hath leues lyke to Cooſte but they be grener then the leues of cooſte &amp; it hath a lytell white flower.<note place="margin">wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a deed chylde.</note> ¶ The vertue is yf a woman be with a deed body it wyll delyuer her therof, this herbe wyll drawe oute a thorne or yron out of a mannes fote or other place and it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Dancus aſinius.</head>
                  <p>DAncus aſinius is an herbe called bryd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt or Danke this herbe hath leues lyke to hemloke and a whyte flower. ¶ The vertu
<pb facs="tcp:3925:16"/>
is that he is good to hele the dropcy and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of venymous beſtes.<note place="margin">dropcy</note> Alſo he openeth the ſtop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pynge of the lyuer and of the mylte.<note place="margin">mylte.</note> Alſo he vnbyndyth a mans wombe and maketh hym laxatyfe,<note place="margin">Laxati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe</note> this herbe groweth in feldes and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his flower lyke to a byrdes neſt and he is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Dancus cleticus.</head>
                  <p>DAncus cleticus is an herbe called The laſſe Tanke this hath leues lyke to wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de popy but the leues be more whytter and he hath a flower y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is purpull color this groweth in wete and is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Dens leonis.</head>
                  <p>DEns leonis is an herbe called Daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or lyons toth this hath leues lyke to hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des toth and he hath a yelowe flower &amp; he hath no brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches but as eche flower ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth out of the moore with a lytel braunche &amp; it droppyth mylke when it is broke. ¶ The vertue is that the more of it is good to hele y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Feuer cotidian and it be dronke with wyne it groweth all aboute.<note place="margin">Feuer.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Dragancia feminea.</head>
                  <p>DRagancia feminea is an herbe called, dragons femall it hath leues like to yue but they haue white ſpectes &amp; it hath a yelowe
<pb facs="tcp:3925:16"/>
ſtalke the lenght of .ii. cubyttes other whyle as it were a croked ſtafe and lyke to a ſnake &amp; ſhe beryth her ſede as it were a cluſter of grapes, and when the ſede is rype it is yelowe this her be groweth in darke places. ¶ The vertu ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of is that yf the ſede be punyd with oyle &amp; put to a mans eron it heleth the akynge of eron.<note place="margin">Eres.</note> Alſo the ioyce of this herbe with a lytyll wole put in to the noſtryll clenſyth the noſe from al fylth.<note place="margin">Noſe.</note> Alſo the more of this herbe punyd with white wyne &amp; ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny,<note place="margin">wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de</note> heleth all woundes &amp; the canker therein. Alſo he frotyth his hande wel with the rote of this herbe he may take eddyrs without any peryll.<note place="margin">For ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re iyen</note> Alſo the ioyce of this rote deſtroyeth the darkenes of the eyen yf they be anoynted therwith Alſo this herbe dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke with wyne ſtyreth a man to lechery.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="E" type="part">
               <head>¶The .v. letter begynneth with. E.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Elena campana.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Lena campana, is an herbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Elen campayne or horſhelme &amp; this herbe hath leues as it we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Comfery, but they be more whitter then the leues of comfery and he hath alonge ſtalke and a yelowe flower. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue is yf a man haue waggynge teth and eate therof faſtyng it wyll faſten his teth.<note place="margin">Teth.</note> Alſo yf
<pb facs="tcp:3925:17"/>
a man drynke this herbe it heleth hym from the ſtone &amp; helpyth hym to make water.<note place="margin">ſtone.</note> Alſo yf it be dronke, it delyueryth a woman of a deade chylde.<note place="margin">laxatyf For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coughe</note> Alſo it hardyth a mans wombe yf it be laxatyfe this herbe helith a man of the coughe this herbe is hote and moyſt it groweth in wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des and feldes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Endiua.</head>
                  <p>ENdiua is an herbe callyd Endyue or horſ thilſtyl, this herbe hath leues lyke to ſow thy ſtyll, this hath pryckes in the rygge &amp; a ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe flower. ¶ The vertu of this herbe is that the ioyce therof medled with hote water and dronke helyth the ſtoppynge of the myl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e and of the lyuer.<note place="margin">For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mylte. Feuer.</note> Alſo it is good to hole the yelowe euyll &amp; the feuer tercian and the hote poſtym. Alſo this herbe ſwagyth the great hete of the lyuer &amp; of the ſtomake &amp; it is cold &amp; moyſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Eruca.</head>
                  <p>ERuca is an herbe callyd Skyrwhy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> this hath leues lyke to byl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, but they be not ſo longe &amp; it hath a great more. ¶ The vertue is that the ioyce of the leues wronge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in a mans mouth helyth all the fore of the mouth.<note place="margin">Stone</note> Alſo it brekyth the ſtone. Alſo the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of this herbe fodde &amp; dronke diſtroyeth black colour.<note place="margin">Colour</note> Alſo it ſtyreth a man moche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heep
<pb facs="tcp:3925:17"/>
and he vſe it. Alſo it helpeth a man to make water.<note place="margin">water. The cough.</note> Alſo the ioyce of this herbe clenſeth a man yf he be auoynted therwith. Alſo the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of this herbe delyueryth men &amp; chyldren fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the coughe, this is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Eufragia.</head>
                  <p>EVfragia is an herbe called eufraſſe, this herbe hath lytel leues lyke to here colourd but they be moche lyke here,<note place="margin">Sore eyen.</note> &amp; he hath a whyte flower. ¶ The vertu is that he is good to hele ſore eyen, this herbe groweth in medes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Ebulus.</head>
                  <p>EBulus is an herbe called walworte, it hath leues ſomdele lyke Erderen and he hathe a longe ſtalke and groweth in feldes.<note place="margin">Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy. For ſcabes.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>¶The vertue is that he is good to dyſtroye the dropſy, and ſcabbes, or tetters. Alſo this herbe draweth wycked humoures out of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Edera.</head>
                  <p>EDera is an herbe called yue, this is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon it dothe couer howſes, &amp; towres, &amp; hath leues lyke to an herbe called bryan, and it bereth fruyte as it were bayes. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue therof is yf it be ſod and layde on a botche it healeth it ſoone.<note place="margin">For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> botche</note> Alſo yf thy heade ake take the ioyce of this herbe with oyle of roſes, and
<pb facs="tcp:3925:18"/>
ſeth them togyther in wyne, and anoynt the hede therwith,<note place="margin">For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heade ache.</note> and thou ſhalt be hole. Alſo yf thou wyl kepe thy heade from akynge in the ſonne, take the leues of this herbe, and pune them ſmall, and then tempre them with eyſell and the oyle of Roſes, and then anoynte thy forheade therwith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Edera terreſtris.</head>
                  <p>EDera terreſtris is an herbe called orpyn, or heyhoue, this hath leues lyke to Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynt,<note place="margin">For to make fleſhe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der.</note> but they be not ſo moche, and hath in the croppe a red flower. ¶ The vertue is yf it be put in potage amonge fleſſhe, he wyll make the fleſſhe tendre and neſſhe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Eborus.</head>
                  <p>EBorus is an herbe called longe wort, or Pelyter of ſpayne, this is lyke to Pede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lion, but the leues of this herbe be not ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſlytte without, and he hath a flower as it were a paſnepe.<note place="margin">Tet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes.</note> ¶ The vertue is that he wyl hele ſcabbes, the morfewe, and tetters. Alſo he heleth the emerawdes, yf it be layde to the place there it bledeth. Alſo he purgeth the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the fleume. Alſo he helpeth the from the tothache yf it be ſod with eyſell,<note place="margin">Toth ache. ſtomac wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. Fleeſe</note> and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de a quantite in your mouth. Alſo this herbe purgeth well the ſtomacke and the wombe.
<pb facs="tcp:3925:18"/>
Alſo the powder of this herbe medled with a lytel growell ſhall ſlee wormes. Alſo the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of this herbe medled with mylke ſhall ſlee flees, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Elabrus.</head>
                  <p>ELabrus is an herbe called Clouentonge, or Pedelyon, this herbe is moche lyke to longeworte, but not ſo flat as be the leues of this herbe, &amp; he hath ſomdele a brode flower, more than a peny, he hath a blacke rote and he is horryble in ſyght. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that yf the powder therof be medled with growel or with meele it wyl ſlee rattes and yf a beeſt pyſſe blode,<note place="margin">Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> gyue hym this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be and he is hole</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Epatica.</head>
                  <p>EPatica is an herbe called liuerwort, this herbe groweth in brymmes of waters, and in welles, and it wyll ioyne to ſtones, and he groweth moche in walles of ſtone, &amp; it hath nother ſtalke, nother flower but ſmall townde leues, &amp; the more the leues be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better to medycynes. ¶ The vertue is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll dyſtroy and clenſe the hardenes of the lyuer.<note place="margin">Lyuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Feuer</note> Alſo the leues therof medeled with ſwynes grece wyll hele woundes. Alſo it is good to hele the Feuer quartayne.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="F" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3925:19"/>
               <head>¶The .vi. letter begynneth with. F.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Famula.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Amula is an herbe called ſperwrot, or lau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecle, this hath leues ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to a ſper hed, it hath a ſtalke, and in the top co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out many ſmall ſtalkes, &amp; it hath a whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te flower, and it groweth in waters. ¶ The vertue therof is that he is good to hele the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers,<note place="margin">Feuer Byles</note> and alſo for to breke botches and byles, and it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Fumus terre.</head>
                  <p>FVmus terre is an herbe called fumetetry this herbe hath leues that ben ſomwhat whyte vnder, and they ben ſmall, and it hath a flowre of purpul colour, and this herbe gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth in ſtalkes, but not ful longe. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue is that he comforteth the ſtomacke.<note place="margin">Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make. water Lyuer Bloud ytchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> Alſo he maketh a man to haue appetyde to mete, it helpeth a man to make water, and it openeth the ſtoppynge of the lyuer, &amp; clereth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes blode. Alſo yf the ioyce therof be dronke it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth ſcabbes and ytchynge, and bladders that ben gendred of wycked humours, and it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:19"/>
                  <head>¶Fragra.</head>
                  <p>FRagra is an herbe called ſtrawbery, and this herbe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon. ¶ The vertue therof is that he is good to dyſtroye a webbe in the iyen. Alſo it is good to hele woundes.<note place="margin">woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. eyen. Mylte</note> Alſo the ioyce medeled with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and dronke he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the akynge of a mannes mylte, this gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in clene and darke places.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Fabaria maior.</head>
                  <p>FAbaria maior is an herbe called brokele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, this herbe hath rownde leues &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che lyke to myntes. ¶ The vertue therof is, yf he be puned with ſhepes talowe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hote in maner of a playſter,<note place="margin">Swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge.</note> and layde to any ſwellynge it wyll hele it, this herbe gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in ſmal brokee, &amp; moſte amonge belton.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Filex.</head>
                  <p>FIlex is an herbe called Ferne, this herbe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, and there be .iii. ſpyces therof, one is called Ferne,<note place="margin">Laxe.</note> and another is called po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipode, another called Oſmonde, and that is the .ii. ſpyces, another is called verrew &amp; that is the .iii. ſpyce,<note place="margin">Broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bones.</note> polipode is good to make a man laxatyue, and groweth in trees, Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monde is good to hele broken bones, and it groweth in dyches and woodes, the .iii. that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> call euer verrew groweth on walles, and
<pb facs="tcp:3925:20"/>
is good to hele the potagre,<note place="margin">Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre.</note> &amp; he maketh ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſenewes, &amp; he groweth in woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, dyches, and feldes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Filipendula.</head>
                  <p>FIlipendula is an herbe that men calleth Filipendull or dropworte, this is lyke to yaron, and he groweth next the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, the leues be more than the leues of yaron, it hath a ſmall ſtalke, and a flower ſomdele whyte, and in the more ſmall pelettes lyke yſhape as it were ſmall pelettes rownde. ¶ The vertue is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll deſtroy wycked wyndes aboute the lyuer and the mylte.<note place="margin">Lyuer</note> Alſo he helpeth to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the ſtone,<note place="margin">ſtone.</note> it groweth in holowe places, and drye, and it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Feniculum.</head>
                  <p>FEniculum is an heebe that men calleth Fenell, this herbe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ynoughe.</p>
                  <p>¶The vertue is, the ſede when it is drye, it diſtroyeth wynde in the ſtomacke.<note place="margin">Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make.</note> Alſo it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth a mannes ſtomacke. Alſo he openeth the ſtoppynge of the raynes &amp; of the bladder. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of this herbe ſtilled in to a mans iye doth away the webbe.<note place="margin">venym</note> Alſo yf if be dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with wyne,<note place="margin">wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> it dyſtroyeth all maner of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nym. Alſo the ioyce dropped in to the eres ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wormes, that ben within. Alſo yf it be
<pb facs="tcp:3925:20"/>
dronke with wyne, it heleth the dropſy.<note place="margin">Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy.</note> Alſo it heleth all maner of ſwellynges. Alſo yf he be dronke with wyne or water, it maketh a womans mylke to wax. Alſo yf he be dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with wyne it kepeth from caſtynge. Alſo yf he be medled with oyle it wyl hele y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of a mans yerde.<note place="margin">Swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge.</note> Alſo yf thou wyl be ſteryed to lecherye, take and drynke the ſede therof with good wyne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Faxmus.</head>
                  <p>FAxmus is an herbe called hertwort or odobrame, this hath leues yſhape as a hert and hath a flower as were bugle, and a ſhorte ſtalke. ¶ The vertue is yf he be broke and layde to a ſore it heleth anone,<note place="margin">A ſore</note> this groweth in feldes and medowes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Finiculus porcinus.</head>
                  <p>FIniculus porcinus is an herbe called ſwynes fenel or worme ſede, this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be hath ſmall leues lyke to yaron, and of a ſtalke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge many braunches it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vpon walles, &amp; hath ſmall coddes and ſmall red ſede. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is,<note place="margin">wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> yf a man ete the ſede therof, it diſtroyeth and ſleyeth the wormes within the wombe, and it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Febrifuga.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3925:21"/>FEbrifuga is called fetherfoy or vethur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foye, this herbe hath many ſtalkes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge out of one ſtalke, and it hath a whyte flower as it were Mayes. ¶ The vertue is that he wyl comforte the ſtomacke.<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> Alſo it ſwageth the feuer cotydyan. Alſo it is good to heale the crampe that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of a colde ſtomacke.<note place="margin">Feuer. Cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe</note> Alſo yf this herbe be puned and layde to a ſore that is bytten with a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymous worme or beeſt it ſhall be hole. Alſo this herbe tempered with eyſell doth awaye the morfew.<note place="margin">Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fewe.</note> Alſo yf this be puned and layde to a wounde, in the whiche is broken bones, it ſhal hele the bones.<note place="margin">woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> Alſo the rote of this her be is good to ſtaunche the blody me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſon, this is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Filago.</head>
                  <p>FIlago is an herbe called felde worte, this herbe hath leues a lytell enlong, and it is lyke to hore hounde, it is a lytell herbe and it groweth in wete.<note place="margin">Eyen.</note> His water is good for eyen</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Flamula minor.</head>
                  <p>FLa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mula minor is an herbe called the leſſe ſperwort, it hath leues as it were graſſe, but it is ſharpe as it were a ſpere.<note place="margin">For bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyuge.</note> ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of this herbe is if it be puned and layde to a hande that is byte, it ſhall be hole anone.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="G" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3925:21"/>
               <head>¶The .vii. letter begynneth with. G.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Granum.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ranum is an herbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gromell, or lytel wale, this hath leues that ben par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te enlonge, and hath a lytell whyte ſede ſhape as a ſtone that men call mariery perle. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he is good to hele the ſtone,<note place="margin">ſtone.</note> and the euyl of the bledder, this herbe maketh a man to make water, and this is hote &amp; dry.<note place="margin">water.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Geneſcula.</head>
                  <p>GEneſcula is an herbe called Geneſtre, or brome, this hath leues lyke to Spy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurnell, and they ben a lytell longer, and it hath a yelowe flower. ¶ The vertue is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is good to knyt bones &amp; ſynewes togyther.<note place="margin">bones.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Genciana.</head>
                  <p>GEnciana is an herbe called bladmoyne or felde wort. ¶ The vertue of this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be is that he clenſeth the ſtoppynge of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, the lyuer and the mylte,<note place="margin">Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make.</note> &amp; it be dronke with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and water.<note place="margin">Lyuer For bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge.</note> Alſo it healeth the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of venymous beeſtes. Alſo it delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a woman of a deade chylde, and this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Galanga.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3925:22"/>GAlanga is an herbe that men call Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngale.<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he comforteth the ſtomacke, &amp; it maketh a man to defye his meate.<note place="margin">wicked wynde For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> Alſo it vnbyndeth and letteth out wycked wyndes out of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes body. Alſo it maketh a mannes mouthe ſwete. Alſo it healeth the reynes. Alſo it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a man to haue appetyte to a woman, &amp; it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Granum ſolis.</head>
                  <p>GRanum ſolis is an herbe called wylde Gromell, this hath leues ſomdele lyke to Gromell, and his ſede is lyke ſomdele to that other gromell ſede. Alſo he hath ſomdele ſuche a flower, neuertheles they dyffereth in the ſtalke, for the ſtalke of this herbe is ſharp and it groweth moche in wete.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Gladiolus.</head>
                  <p>GLadiolus is an herbe called Gladyoll, or Gladur, this herbe hath leues like to an herbe called Getus, but it is not ſo grene, it hath a yelow flower &amp; a longe ſtalke,<note place="margin">Laxe.</note> and it groweth in water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Graciadei.</head>
                  <p>GRaciadei is an herbe called graciadei, this hath leues ſomdele lyke to dens de lyon, but the leues of this be ſomwhat ſharp,
<pb facs="tcp:3925:22"/>
and it hath yelowe flowers, and it groweth in drye lande.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Graciadei maior.</head>
                  <p>GRaciadei maior is an herbe called gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciadei the more, this hath leues lyke to cokyll, &amp; it hath a whyte flower, it groweth in drye grounde, and whan that it is broke it droppeth mylke.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="H" type="part">
               <head>¶The .viii. letter begynneth with. H.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Haſtula regia.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aſtula regia is an herbe called wodrofe, it hath leues lyke to croyes wort, and this herbe is ſote in ſauour, and a woman ſmell moche therto it maketh her heade to ake.<note place="margin">mouth</note> ¶ The vertue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is yf the more of it be puned with wyne it ſhall hele ſores of the mouthe.<note place="margin">For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wombe</note> Alſo take the ſede of this herbe and pune it and tempre it with the ſowreſt eyſel that ye can fynde and, drynke it, and it ſhall ſtaunche the flyxe and, harde the wombe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Herba crucita.</head>
                  <p>HErba crucita is an herbe called Eroys worte or Exean, this hath lytell leues
<pb facs="tcp:3925:23"/>
and a ſmall ſtalke,<note place="margin">woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> and alſo a whyte flower. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll hele well woundes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Herba chriſtofori.</head>
                  <p>HErba chriſtofori maſculus is an herbe called herbe chriſtofer male, this herbe hath leues moche lyke to leſſe croweſape, but they ben more whyte and not fully ſo longe, and it groweth in drye grounde, and alſo in watery places,<note place="margin">Peſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</note> and it hath a yelowe flower ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he is good to hele the peſtelence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Herba walteri.</head>
                  <p>HErba walteri is an herbe called herbe water, this hath leues lyke to the leues of Perſely, and the leues be thycke, fat, and tender.<note place="margin">woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll clenſe woundes ond hele them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Herba Roberti.</head>
                  <p>HErba Roberti is an herbe called herbe Robert, this hath leues lyke to herbe Benet,<note place="margin">woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Ka<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ker</note> it hath a ſmall flower that is ſomdele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, it groweth in feledes and in hedges, and in walles. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll hele woundes, and alſo the powder wyll ſlee the Canker.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Herba martis.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3925:23"/>HErba martis is an herbe called morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, this herbe hath leues lyke to a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. M. when he is a capytall letter, &amp; in ſome brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che he hath .ix. leues, and ſome more, and ſome fewer, and bryngeth forth her leues and ſede togyther, this herbe hath many wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vertues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Herba Iohannis.</head>
                  <p>HErba Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis is an herbe called ſaynt Iohanes worte, it hath leues lyke to the leſſe Centory, it hath a yelowe flower and a longe ſtalke, and many ſtalkes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge of one. ¶ The vertue is yf he be in a howſe,<note place="margin">wycked ſpirites</note> he ſuffreth no wycked ſpryte dwell therin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Herba petri.</head>
                  <p>HErba petri is an herbe called cowſlope, this herbe hath leues lyke to herbe x<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for femall, but they be more whyter, and it groweth in medowes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="I" type="part">
               <head>¶The .ix. letter begynneth with. I.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Iuſquiamus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vſquiamus is an herbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bane or He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nebel, this herbe hath leues ſomewhat whyte vnder and the leues be flat a lytell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out as it were ſowthiſtell, it hath a flower ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb facs="tcp:3925:24"/>
whyte, and it hath a great ſtalke &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny braunches commynge out of one more, &amp; it groweth in hye wayes. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that the oyle made therof is good to dyſtroye all maner of gowtes,<note place="margin">gowte.</note> and namely that, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of melancolye. Alſo the ſede of this herbe layde on a ſlayte ſtone and hete with the fyre,<note place="margin">wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. cough.</note> and let it ſmoke in the mannes mouth, it ſleeth wormes in the teth. Alſo he ſwageth the coughe and hote poſtume &amp; hote potagre.<note place="margin">Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre. Toth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ache. woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more is good for the to thach and the ioyce of this is good for all maner of woundes, and the ſede therof ſhulde be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Auguſt. Alſo yf thou caſt the ſede ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the fyre, all the hennes that ben ouer the fyre ſhall fall in to the fyre, and it is colde &amp; drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Iſopus.</head>
                  <p>ISopus is an herbe called Iſope, it hath leues lyke to Sauery, but they be not ſo brode, and he flowreth as doth Sauery. ¶ The vertue therof is that the ioyce therof medled with eyſell,<note place="margin">A ſore mouth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> and put in a ſore mouthe heleth it. Alſo it ſleeth wormes in the wombe and maketh the wombe neſſhe. Alſo yf it be dronke grene or elles the powder, it maketh a man well colowred, it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Ireoſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3925:24"/>IReoſe is an herbe called Saue, and his leues be lyke to flowerdelyce, and it hath a whyte flower, and groweth in water.<note place="margin">Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes. The couhe. venym The cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe. A dead chylde.</note> ¶ The vertue therof is that he wyll hele the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of the ſenewes. Alſo it dyſtroyeth the coughe. Alſo yf it be dronke with wyne it dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth the wycked humoures of the breeſt. Alſo it helpeth the bytyng of venymous bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes or wormes. Alſo it dyſtroieth the crampe Alſo it delyuereth a woman of a deade chylde this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Iris.</head>
                  <p>IRis is an herbe called flowerdelyſe, and it is lyke to Saue almoſte in all maner fetures, but this herbe hath a flower al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte of purpull colour, this groweth in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and gardaynes, and he hath the ſame ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues that Saue hath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Iua.</head>
                  <p>IVa is an herbe called Iue, this herbe hath a rote euen downe to the grounde gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wynge,<note place="margin">Swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge.</note> &amp; it hath ſmall leues growynge euen by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. ¶ The vertue is yf a man haue a ſore ſwellyng aboute his eres, take this herbe cumbonfitatibus of her in wyne &amp; oyle and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn,<note place="margin">Eares.</note> and than make a playſter therof and lay to the eares and it ſhall hele them. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:3925:25"/>
ſo take the knobbes of the rote and drye them and clenſe them, &amp; they haue vertue to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laxatyue,<note place="margin">Laxe.</note> and it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Iaſia alba.</head>
                  <p>IAſia alba is an herbe called wylde Tanſey or goſe graſſe, but they be more whyter, &amp; it hath a yelow flower, &amp; it groweth downe by the grownde, as doth the ſtrawberyes.</p>
                  <p>¶The vertue of this herbe is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge of a mans lymmes,<note place="margin">Clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge.</note> it groweth in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, lees, woodes, and wayes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Iaſia nigra.</head>
                  <p>IAſia nigra is an herbe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men call mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felon, or bulwede, or yrenharde, or knop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wede, this hath leues lyke to ſcabyous, &amp; it hath a purpull colour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Ippia maior.</head>
                  <p>IPpia maior is an herbe called pympernel, or ſelf hele, or wayworte, or more croppe, this hath leues lyke to chycke wede, but the leues of this ben leſſe, and it hath a flower of purpull coloure,<note place="margin">woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. venym Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</note> &amp; it groweth in wete. ¶The vertue of this herbe is that he is good to hele wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and to deſtroy venym, &amp; is good for the Poſtume, and to hele the fore iyen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Ippia minor.</head>
                  <p>IPpia minor is an herbe that men call chyk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
<pb facs="tcp:3925:25"/>
this herbe hath leues lyke to pympernel, &amp; it hath a whyte flower, and it groweth in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daynes and in feldes. ¶The vertue of this herbe is,<note place="margin">Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes.</note> ſeth it in ronnynge water and waſſhe your ſcabby handes therin often tymes, and they ſhall be hole.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="L" type="part">
               <head>¶The .x. letter begynneth with. L.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Laniſticum.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Aniſticum is an her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be called lonage, this her be hath leues lyke to Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage, but they be ſomde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le more, &amp; it hath a longe ſtalke, and it is ſtronge in ſauour. ¶The vertue is in the ſede of her. Alſo the mores therof dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke with wyne, is good for the ſtomacke,<note place="margin">Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke.</note> and for good dygeſtynge, this is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lingua ceruina.</head>
                  <p>LIngua ceruina is an herbe called hertes tongue, this hath leues lyke to the tonge of a harte, and it groweth in walles and drye places, &amp; hath no ſede, nor flower, nor ſtalke. ¶The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe the poſtume and breke it,<note place="margin">Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me.</note> yf it be ſode with oyle of Roſes. Alſo yf it be dronke with olde
<pb facs="tcp:3925:26"/>
wyne,<note place="margin">wombe cough.</note> it hardeneth the wombe. Alſo it healeth a man of the coughe, this is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lilium.</head>
                  <p>LIlium is an herbe that men call Lylye. ¶The vertu of this herbe is that yf thou pune it with talowe, and ſeeth it with oyle, &amp; laye it to the place there as the colde poſtume is,<note place="margin">Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me.</note> it ſhall rype hym and breke hym. Alſo take the rotes of lylye, &amp; the rotes of the rede docke and the more of louage, and put all theſe in wyne and oyle, the ſpace of .ii. dayes &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward let it ſeth and clenſe it, &amp; do therto waxe and oyle, &amp; make anoyntment &amp; that is good to hele the ſores and hardenes of a mannes mylte.<note place="margin">Mylte</note> Alſo take the knobbes of the rotes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lylye and roſte them amonge the coles, and take oyle Olyue &amp; anoynte there as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſore is.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Liguſtrum.</head>
                  <p>LIguſtrum is an herbe called prymeroſe. ¶The vertue of this herbe is good for to make potage. Alſo the ioyce put in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes noſe wyll dyſtroy the Megrym.<note place="margin">Megri</note> Alſo the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the rote is ſoden in is good to vnſtop the conduytes of vryne.<note place="margin">vryne.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lingua bouis.</head>
                  <p>LIngua bouis is an herbe called Langde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>befe. ¶The vertue of this herbe is good
<pb facs="tcp:3925:26"/>
to do awaye the rede colour of a man.<note place="margin">Color.</note> Alſo yf it be dronken it doth awaye the cardyacle and other wycked humours in a mannes lunges.<note place="margin">lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges.</note> ¶ Alſo the ioyce of this herbe dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke with hote water,<note place="margin">wytte.</note> maketh a man to haue a good mynde &amp; good wyt, this muſt be gathered in Iune or in Iuly, and this is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lingua ſerpentis maior.</head>
                  <p>LIngua ſerpentis maior is an herbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Adder tongue, this herbe hath leues lyke to Affodyll, but they be more grene, &amp; alſo more ſharpe in the ende, this muſt be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in the moneth of Apryll.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lyngua ſerpentis minor.</head>
                  <p>LIngua ſerpentis minor is an herbe called the leſſe Adder tongue, this herbe hath le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues ſomwhat lyke to Pygyll, and it hath a ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe flower, and out of the ſtalke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches, and it groweth in woodes</p>
                  <p>¶The vertue of this herbe is good to lay to a cut, yf it be bruſed and layde therto.<note place="margin">A cut.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lingua canis.</head>
                  <p>LIngua canis is an herbe called houndes tongue. ¶The vertue of this herbe is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is good to dyſtroy the coughe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and it wyll rype a botche.<note place="margin">cough. Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> Alſo this herbe eaten is good for ſhakynge of the hede, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:3925:27"/>
the throte and the breth ſmothe &amp; ſouple.<note place="margin">flux of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be.</note> Alſo it is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flux of the wombe yf thy fete bewaſſhed in the water that it is foden in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lingua hircina.</head>
                  <p>LIngua hircina is an herbe called Bucke ſhorne, or ſwyneſkerce this herbe hath le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues flatered as it were an hertes horne, and it groweth crepynge by the grounde, &amp; it hath a lytell whyte flower, it groweth in watery pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> ¶The vertue is that it clenſeth the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke and refreyneth the great hete and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the brennynge of fyre,<note place="margin">burni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of fyre</note> yf that it be ſoden and layde therto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lupinus.</head>
                  <p>LVpinus is an herbe called Lupyne, this herbe hath leues lyke to fyue leued gras, the Lupyne hath .vi. leues and it hath a whyte flower, and a whyte ſede that is ſomwhat bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, &amp; it bereth coddes ſomwhat lyke to bene coddes. ¶The vertue of this herbe is, yf a man haue wormes in his wombe, take the ſede and make meele therof, &amp; the ioyce of worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wode and ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, &amp; make a cake therof and ete it,<note place="margin">lyuer.</note> and it vnbyndeth the ſtoppynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuer and of the mylte. Alſo it is good to dyſtroye the dropſy.<note place="margin">Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy.</note> Alſo take the ſame meele and the ioyce of arſmerte, and make therof paſte &amp; lay
<pb facs="tcp:3925:27"/>
it to thy eares,<note place="margin">wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> &amp; it ſhall kyll the wormes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them or yf thou make a cake therof and hete it, it wyll do the ſame. Alſo yf thou wylt take the ioyce of Lekes,<note place="margin">Eares</note> and tempre it with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mele and put it in thy eres, it ſhall clenſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from all wycked humours and ſtynkyng. Alſo take the ſame meele and tempre it with oyle,<note place="margin">poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</note> and it wyl breke &amp; rype all maner of poſtumes. And this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Labrum veneris.</head>
                  <p>LAbrum veneris is an herbe that men cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Sowthy ſtyll. ¶The vertue of this herbe is this, yf a man haue a hote feuer,<note place="margin">Feuer</note> take the ioyce therof &amp; tempre it with hote water, and let hym drynke it and he ſhal be hole. Alſo yf a man haue venym within hym,<note place="margin">venym</note> take this herbe and drye it &amp; make powder therof, and do the powder in good wyne, and lette hym drynke it, &amp; it wyll caſt vp all the venym, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lauendula.</head>
                  <p>LAuendula is an herbe called Laua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, yf this be ſoden in water,<note place="margin">Palſie</note> &amp; gyuen to a man that hath the palſye, it wyll hele hym, and this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lactuca.</head>
                  <p>LActuca is an herbe that is called Lettyſe,
<pb facs="tcp:3925:28"/>
or ſtope worte. ¶The vertue of this herbe is this, yf it be eaten rawe or ſoden it engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth good bloude.<note place="margin">bloude</note> Alſo this herbe ſoden with a lytell eyſell and Saffron &amp; than dronken, it helpeth a man that is ſtopped in the lyuer and in the mylt.<note place="margin">lyuer. Mylt.</note> Alſo yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not ſlepe, take the ſede of this herbe and ſtampe it to powder and tempre it with womans mylke &amp; make a playſter therof on lynt,<note place="margin">Slepe</note> &amp; lay it to the temples of thy heade, and thou ſhalt ſlepe well, or elles drynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> powder therof with mylke. Alſo take the ſede and tempre it with oyle of roſes, and make a playſter &amp; lay it to thy ſtomacke,<note place="margin">Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me. Flyx.</note> &amp; it is good to dyſtroye the hote poſtume. Alſo drynke the ioyce of this herbe, or powder the ſede for it is good to hele the flyx, but who y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vſeth this herbe ouermoche, it wyll dyſtroye theyr ſyght, this herbe is colde &amp; ſom moyſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lactuca ſiluatica.</head>
                  <p>LActuca ſyluatica is an herbe called wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Lettyſe, this herbe hath leues lyke to the thiſtell, and they be ſharpe &amp; kent, &amp; it hath a flower of purpull colour, and it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in feldes and in whete, this herbe is hote and drye. ¶The vertue of this herbe is that it taketh away the dymnes of the iyes,<note place="margin">Eyes.</note> medle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of this herbe with wyne or ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and the
<pb facs="tcp:3925:28"/>
gall of an Auſtour, or other foule of pray, &amp; put it all medled in a glaſſe, and put it in thy iyes .iii. tymes in a day or more, and in ſhorte ſpace thy iyes ſhall be clere,<note place="margin">Eyes.</note> for it is a ſoueray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne medicyne. And bycauſe this herbe is good for to clere the ſyght, ſome ſay that the Egle eateth this herbe when that he wyll flee hye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lactuca leporica.</head>
                  <p>LActuca leporica is an herbe called Hare thyſtell, this herbe hath leues lyke vnto Sowthyſtell, but the leues be not ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented, it droppeth mylke.<note place="margin">Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> ¶The vertue of this herbe is thus, yf a hare eate of this herbe in ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer whan he is mad, he ſhall be hole. Alſo take this herbe &amp; lay it to a mannes ſyde when he ſlepeth,<note place="margin">Feuer</note> or els that he knowe not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and it wyll hele hym of the feuers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lollium.</head>
                  <p>LOllium is an herbe that men cal Cokle. ¶The vertue of this herbe is thus, yf it be dronken with Radyſſhe, &amp; a lytel ſalt,<note place="margin">Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ker woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. ſtomac water. Eyes.</note> it is good to hele the Canker, or other wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des in peryll. Alſo it is good to comforte the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke and the lyuer. Alſo it wyll vnbynde the wormes in a mans ſtomacke. Alſo it helpeth a man to make water, and it is good for ſore eyes. Alſo ſubfumygacyon therof wyll make
<pb facs="tcp:3925:29"/>
a woman to bere her chylde withoute any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll or harme.<note place="margin">chylde</note> Alſo it wyll aſſwage the great paynes of akynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lypur,<note place="margin">lypur.</note> it is hote &amp; dry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Laparium rubeum.</head>
                  <p>LAparium rubeum is an herbe called red docke,<note place="margin">Toth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. The kinges euyll.</note> yf that a man take the ioyce ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of &amp; holde it in his mouth, it wyl aſſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge the tothache. Alſo yf a man haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges euyll take this herbe and ſeth it in wyne, and ſtrayne it and gyue it hym to drynke, and he ſhal be hole yf he vſe it oft. Alſo yf that a man rubbe hym with the ioyce,<note place="margin">ytchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</note> it doth awaye euyll ytchynges. Alſo this herbe is good to delyuer wyndes that be ſtopped in a mans ſtomacke by balkynge.<note place="margin">ſtomac Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes. botche. wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be.</note> Alſo this herbe is good to make ſcabbes and botches rype. Alſo it is good to make a man to haue a harde wombe, &amp; this her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Linum.</head>
                  <p>LInum is an herbe that men call Flex, &amp; it is good yf a man take the ſede therof, &amp; ſeth it in water, it maketh a man laxatyue, &amp; it is good to make a plaiſter therof for akyng ſores. Alſo there is another ſpyce therof that is called Cuſtula, and it is named i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> englyſſhe Dodure,<note place="margin">to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge.</note> &amp; it groweth amonge flex. ¶The vertue of this herbe is that he good to purge a
<pb facs="tcp:3925:29"/>
man of the coloure. Alſo yf a great quantyte therof be taken, and ſoden in Myrre and oyle togyther, &amp; a playſter made therof,<note place="margin">Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> it is good for the raynes and for the breeſt, &amp; for other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge lymbes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Lauriola<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </head>
                  <p>LAuriola is an herbe that men call lawrel ¶The vertue of this herbe is that it wyl make a man laxatyue,<note place="margin">Laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue. to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge.</note> &amp; it is good to purge a man of fleume and of coloure, it is good for a man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may not eate, for yf the ioyce therof be put i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his eres, or yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd herbe be ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ped, and a ſuppoſitory be made therof &amp; layde on cotton, it wyll hele it.<note place="margin">Eres. Humo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res.</note> Alſo for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> here not well put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce in to his eres, &amp; yf there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> humours it wyll drye them, and it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Licoriſa.</head>
                  <p>LIcoriſa is an herbe that men call Lyco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rote of this herbe is ſwete, and it moyſteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyndly hete of a man &amp; it is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coughe. Alſo yf it be ſoden in water,<note place="margin">Hete. cough. thurſte</note> it wyll dyſtroy a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes thurſte. Alſo it maketh a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes breſt, his throte, &amp; his lunges moyſte and in good tempre.<note place="margin">Breeſt Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me.</note> Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lycoryſe is ſoden in, is good agaynſt all ſyckenes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breſt and for the poſtume of the rybbes called
<pb facs="tcp:3925:30"/>
Pleuereſy, it is colde and moyſte.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="M" type="part">
               <head>¶The .xi. letter begynneth with. M.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Millefolio minor.</head>
                  <p>MIllefolio minor is an her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be that is called the leſſe Myl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foyle, there is no dyffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of kynde nor vertue betwene myl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>foyle the leſſe, and Mylfoyle the more, ſaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more groweth in gardaynes, and the leſſe in wylde places they be both of one ſtrenght. ¶The vertue of this herbe ſhall be declared in Mylfoyle the more folowynge by lettre.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Mercurialis.</head>
                  <p>MErcurialis is an herbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men cal Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curye. ¶The vertue of this herbe is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is good yf a man haue akynge in his wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be gyue hym to drynke the ioyce and he ſhall be hole,<note place="margin">wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be.</note> it wyll clenſe the ſtomacke, and the ſede wyl do the ſame.<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> Alſo the ioyce tempred with whyte wyne is good to hele ſore iyes, and yf a worme or other vermyn haue bytten a man,<note place="margin">Eyes. Byti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> take the ioyce and warme it, &amp; waſſhe it. Alſo yf there be any wormes cropen in to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes eres, take the ioyce and warme it &amp; put it in to his eares,<note place="margin">Eares</note> &amp; he ſhall be hole, this is hote &amp; drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Menta.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3925:30"/>MEnta to an herbe that men call Mynte ¶The vertue of this herbe is that yf it be ofte eaten,<note place="margin">wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. botche. ſwelli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> it wyl ſlee the wormes in a mannes wombe. Alſo yf a man haue bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or other rennynges or ſwellynges in his heade, take this herbe and ſtampe it, &amp; lay it to the ſore, and it wyll hele it. Alſo yf a mannes toth or the fleſſh of the toth ake or ſtynke:<note place="margin">Totha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che.</note> take this herbe and ſeth it in whyte wyne &amp; in eyſel and take that lycour &amp; waſſhe his mouth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, than take the powder of the herbe &amp; rub well his teth therwith,<note place="margin">mouth Tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> and he ſhal haue a ſwete ſmellynge mouth. Alſo take thou this herbe &amp; eyſell &amp; make ſauce, &amp; it wyll make the to haue a talent to thy mete. Alſo when there ſhall be gyuen any medycyne to deſtroye venym, it wyll be good to be gyuen with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of this herbe, for it hath many vertues,<note place="margin">venym</note> and namely for venym, there be many ſpices therof, &amp; it is hote and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Menta romana.</head>
                  <p>MEnta romana is an herbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men call whyte Mynte. ¶The vertue of this herbe is that the ioyce therof wyll ſlee wormes in a mannes wombe.<note place="margin">wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be.</note> Alſo the ioyce wyll ſlee wormes in the noſe thyrlles of a man.<note place="margin">Noſe.</note> Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> powder therof caſte in a mannes meate, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:3925:31"/>
make hym well to defye hys meate. Alſo the ioyce dronke ſleeth the wormes of the wombe yf it be dropped in the eres,<note place="margin">wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> it ſleeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wormes</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Malua.</head>
                  <p>MAlua is an herbe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men call Mallowe. ¶The vertue of this herbe is good yf the leues be ſtamped and layde to a mannes ſtomacke,<note place="margin">poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</note> it wyll breke a hote poſtume in the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge, or els medle this herbe with freſhe ſwynes grece, and lay it on a hote tyle, &amp; laye it all hote to the poſtume, and it ſhall rype it, and breke it. Alſo it is good to dyſtroy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hard<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of a mans lyuer and mylte.<note place="margin">Lyuer</note> Alſo it wyll make a man laxatyue, and it is good for play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, it is colde and moyſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Morell or nyghtſhadowe.</head>
                  <p>MOrell is an herbe that men call nyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowe, this herbe is colde &amp; drye in the .ii. degre, the leues, the braunches, and the fruytes therof be ryght good &amp; beſt when they be grene. ¶The vertue is they be good for ſtoppynge of the ſplen and the lyuer,<note place="margin">Splen lyuer. Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me.</note> and beſt for the Iau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſe to drynke the ioyce of it with a lytell Ruberbe. Alſo it is good for a poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in the ſtomacke, in the bowels, or in the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſethe the ioyce therof with barly water &amp; drynke it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:31"/>
                  <head>¶Maſtyke.</head>
                  <p>MAſtyke is an herbe that men call gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me and it is hote &amp; drye in the .ii. degre, &amp; it is a gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of a tre growynge in a parte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countre of Grece, in the latter ende of Dere the men of that countre ſlytte the trees, &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make the grownde clene all aboute &amp; laye clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes rounde aboute the trees, or ſome other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge to kepe the gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me from the grounde in cloſynge of it, to knowe which is beſt, to take the beſt is whyte and clere, the whyte coloure is next the beſt, and that is medled with earth and ſomwhat darke,<note place="margin">Clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge.</note> the beſt maſtyke hath ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of conſtraynyng, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortynge, clenſyng, and loſynge ef humours dyſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng from the heade aboue to the iyes and to the teth, &amp; for the diſeaſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temples made of an aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng wynde from the ſtomacke to the hede. Take powder of maſtyke with whyte ſwete wyne, &amp; the whyte of an egge, and medle them well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther, &amp; ye wyll ye may put in frankenſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and playſter it to the temples. Alſo ſeth maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyke in water and drynke it &amp; it wyll comfort well the ſtomacke and make good degeſtion,<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> &amp; it comforteth and relaxeth the ſtomacke, and put to it fenel ſede, and it putteth out wynde out of the ſtomacke. Alſo a playſter made of
<pb facs="tcp:3925:32"/>
Maſtyke and bole armonyake, &amp; the whyte of an egge and vynegre, &amp; laye it on the forke of the ſtomacke or breſt,<note place="margin">Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryke.</note> it wyll conſtrayne well the coloryke vanyte. Alſo ſeth maſtyke in ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne water &amp; drynke it warme, &amp; this medycyne is very good for the flux of the wombe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of a ſharpe lax that was taken before to ſtop hym.<note place="margin">Flux.</note> Alſo boyle Maſtyke in rayne water or Roſe water, with two or thre cloues, and drynke it warme, and that comforteth the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myte and the flux of the wombe that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of ſharpnes and vyolence of the medycyne. Alſo Maſtyke muſt haue but lytell boylynge for hurtynge of his vertue, and it ſhuld be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen warme, for it conſtrayneth the more wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it is gyuen warme, than whan it is ouer moche hote.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Magerum.</head>
                  <p>MAgerum is an herbe that is hote &amp; dry in the ſeconde degre, the flowers and leues be vſed in medycynes, &amp; it ſhulde be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer whan it flowreth, and drye it in the ſhadowe, and it may be kepte a yere. ¶The vertue of this herbe is good in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge, loſynge, conſumynge, &amp; of clenſynge yf the powder of it be dronken in wyne, or els boyle the powder of it in wyne,<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> and it wyll
<pb facs="tcp:3925:32"/>
hete well the ſtomake. Alſo it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forteth the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtyon. Alſo take the leues and flowers of Magerum, and pune them a lytell &amp; make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hote in a panne,<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> and lay it to the greuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; it taketh awaye the dyſeaſe in the ſtomacke that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of wynde.<note place="margin">rewme</note> Alſo for the rewme in the heade, take this herbe &amp; bynde it warme about thy heade.<note place="margin">mother</note> Alſo it dryeth the mother and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth the ſuperfluyte of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Myllefolium maior.</head>
                  <p>MIllefolium maior or yarow is an her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be that kynge Achylles dyd fynde, &amp; therwith heled his men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were wounded with yron. ¶The vertue of this herbe is good for woundes,<note place="margin">woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> ſtampe this herbe with ſwynes gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and playſter it to the wounde, &amp; it ſhall hele it, &amp; the ſame is good for an ache in the breſte or ſyde, it is good for hym that may not pyſſe take the ioyce of this herbe and vyneger and drynke it, &amp; merueylouſly it helpeth a wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that hath taken colde, ſtampe this herbe in but<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, and lay it to the wounde,<note place="margin">Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke.</note> &amp; it wyll hele it well. Alſo to degeſt the ſtomacke or that lyeth therin, take the ioyce of it, and medle it with water and ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nye, and drynke it warme. Alſo it is good for dyſeaſes in the body,<note place="margin">Body:</note> take the powder and medle it with wyne or with good
<pb facs="tcp:3925:33"/>
ale,<note place="margin">Harte. Heade. For bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge of wod doggꝭ. for wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> and drynke it &amp; it helpeth moche. Alſo it is good for the herte brennynge. Alſo for the heade ache ſtampe this herbe, and playſter it to the heade. Alſo for bytynge of a wood dog ſtampe this herbe with the graynes of whete, and it healeth it. Alſo for hym that maye not holde his meate, take &amp; ſtampe this herbe with wyne, and drynke it warme.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Mother worte.</head>
                  <p>MOther worte or mogworte, this herbe is called in latyn Artemeſia, and it is hote and drye in the thyrde degre, this herbe helpeth a woman to conceyue a chylde, cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeth the mother,<note place="margin">chylde.</note> and maketh a woman to haue her flowers, and it dyſtroyeth the emerawdes on this maner. Fyrſte it muſt be gathered, than take the powder of motherworte,<note place="margin">Pap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. a dead chylde.</note> and of Hore hounde togyther, and ſtrawe it on the pappes Alſo yf a chylde be deade in the mothers wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, take motherwort, and ſtampe it ſmall, and make a playſter therof and laye it to her wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be all colde, and with the grace of God ſhe ſhall haue delyueraunce without perell, it is good for the ſtone and the grauell in the raynes of a man or of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">ſtone.</note> yf a man bere this herbe vpon hym, there ſhal no venymous beeſt gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue hym. It is good for the yelowe Iaundes &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:3925:33"/>
it be dronken with wyne,<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> for it comforteth the ſtomacke, &amp; maketh a man or woman to haue a good coloure.<note place="margin">colour. bowels</note> Agaynſt ache of the bowelles powdre of mugwort dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny eaſeth greatly, and is good for diuers ſyckeneſſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Maces.</head>
                  <p>MAces is a ſpyce that is called Mace, this ſpyce is hote and drye in the ſoco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de degre, maces is the rynde or huſke that gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth aboute the Nutmege, as the rynde gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth aboute the haſell nutte, it may be kepte. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> x. yere in his vertue, it is comfortyng, dyſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, &amp; conſumyng, the knowledge of fyne maces is thus, it ſhulde be in coloure lyke to fyne golde, or elles lyke to golde that ſyluer is gylt with, the which hath a ſharpe talage with a bytternes, and it loketh lyke to earthe, it is to be refuſed, for it hath no ſharpe ſauour, for a colde ſtomacke that maye not defye nor degeſte wel,<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> take maces &amp; boyle them in wyne and drynke it. Alſo a good playſter the which is beſt for a feble ſtomacke, and make powder of maſtyke and of maces, &amp; medle them with oyle of Roſes and wexe, and make a playſter therof and lay it on the ſtomacke of the ſycke perſon. Alſo to cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe the brayne of ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humoures, take a quantite of Maces,<note place="margin">brayn.</note> &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:3925:34"/>
chewe them well in thy mouth, and holde them there a whyle, and that ſhall loſe the feumoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of humours that ryſe vp to the brayne,<note place="margin">brayne</note> and purge the ſuperfluyte of it. Alſo for feblenes of the ſtomacke and the lyuer of a colde cauſe,<note place="margin">ſtomac Lyuer</note> and for the colyke, and for the dyſeaſes of the ſpyrytuall membres, or flewme, boyle maces in the ioyce of fenell, &amp; in the ende of the boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge put in a lytell wyne, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrayne it and drynke it for it is the beſt remedye for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd dyſeaſes. Alſo for the ache of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hert, vſe powdre of maces in thy meates and drynkes.<note place="margin">y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Menta.</head>
                  <p>MEnta is an herbe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is called red mynt it is hote &amp; dry in the ſeconde degre, &amp; there be .ii. other myntes, but I meane howſe mintes the whiche properly is ſayde gardaine myntes, for that moſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly is in medyci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes both grene &amp; drye, for great holſomnes it ſhulde be dryed in a ſhadowe place, and ſo it wyl be kepte a yere in great vertue, to dyſſolue or loſe, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume of his proper qualyte, &amp; to comforte of his ſwete ſauoure. ¶The vertue is this,<note place="margin">mouth</note> for the ſtynkyng of the mouth &amp; fylth of the gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes &amp; of the teth, waſſhe thy mouth and gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes with vynegre that myntes be ſod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den in, and after rub hym with the powdre of
<pb facs="tcp:3925:34"/>
myntes, or with dry myntes to prouoke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petyte when an impedyment of the ſtomacke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of colde humours beyng in the mouth of the ſtomacke, make a ſalue of myntes and vynegre with a lytell ſynamum and peper, &amp; vſe it wel agaynſt vomytes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of feble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ſtomacke or of colde cauſes,<note place="margin">Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke.</note> ſethe myntes in ſauge water and vynegre, &amp; depe it in and lay it on the mouth of the ſtomacke with the myntes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be ſoden therin. Alſo gyue to the pacient to eate of the ſame myntes for the ſyncopyne, and febleneſſe in feuers, and without feuers, or of medycyne, or of what cauſe it be, ſtampe myntes with vynegre, and a lytell wyne yf the pacyent be without feuer, and yf he be with feuer, ſtampe myntes with vynegre alone, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make a toſte of ſowre bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, &amp; toſte it well tyll it be almoſte brent, then put it in that lycour, and let it lye therin tyl it be well ſoked, than put it in to his noſe &amp; rub his lyppes, and gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, teth, &amp; temples, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and bynde it to the poulſe vaynes of his armes, and let the pacyent eate the moyſtnes that is left and ſwalowe it in. For to clenſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother, take the tender croppes of myntes,<note place="margin">to cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe</note> &amp; ſethe them in water or wyne, and playſter it to the ſhare, &amp; to the raynes. Agaynſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge
<pb facs="tcp:3925:35"/>
in a womans breſte, take the ſmall ſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of myntes and ſeth them in wyne &amp; oyle, and playſter it aboute the teares. Alſo be it knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that whan any medycyne ſhuld be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen agaynſt venym, it ſhulde be gyuen with the ioyce of myntes, for myntes haue a maner of ſtrength of drawynge out venym,<note place="margin">venym</note> or els it ſhulde be gyuen with wyne that myntes haue be ſoden in.<note place="margin">Splen Lyuer</note> For ſtoppynge of the ſplen &amp; the lyuer, and of the wayes of the vryne of a colde humour &amp; a hote without feuer, take the ioyce of myntes alone, or myntes ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in wyne, or the ioyce of myntes medled with honny, and gyue it to the pacyent.<note place="margin">wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> To ſlee wormes in the bely, take the ioyce of myntes and drynke it, and thou ſhalte be hole. Alſo the ioyce of myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes ſleeth wormes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eares.<note place="margin">A tet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> For a tetter take the ioyce of myntes, &amp; put therto brymſtone &amp; vynegre, and medle them well togyther, and anoynt the tetter therwith and thou ſhalt be hole.<note place="margin">woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> For a wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in the heade, ſtampe myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and lay on the wounde. &amp;c. For payne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyde,<note place="margin">Syde.</note> take myntes and ſeth them in olde wyne or ale, &amp; with it ſtampe .xviii. graynes of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and drynke it in the nyght, &amp; it wyll eaſe the of thy payne.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="N" type="part">
               <head>¶The .xii. letter begynneth with. N.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:35"/>
                  <head>¶Nux muſcata.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Vx muſcata is a herbe the which is called a Nutmeg, it is hote and drye in the ſeconde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre, the beſt groweth in ynde, &amp; in the tyme of his rypynge it is gathered and ſeuen yere it may be kept, they that be playne and heuy after theyr kynde, be beſt to be choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And when they be broken they fall not to pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, but they haue a ſwete and ſharpe ſauour, yf they lacke any of theſe aforeſayd, they be not good for medycyne.<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge.</note> ¶The vertue is of comfortynge by his ſwete ſauoure. For cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; feblenes of degeſtion of the ſtomacke, take in the mornyng halfe a nutmeg or a hole nutmeg, &amp; eate it.<note place="margin">ſtomac Lyuer.</note> Alſo for a colde ſtomacke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is feble of degeſtyon, and for the lyuer, gyue hym wyne that nutmeg is boyled in. Alſo for the ſame boyle nutmegꝭ &amp; Maſtyke in wyne and drynke it, this is good for the dyſeaſes in the ſtomacke, &amp; in the bowels to breke wynde.<note place="margin">bowels</note> Alſo in the recourynge of a ſyckenes to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte the ſpyrytual membres, boyle Nutmegꝭ and Maſtyke in wyne, &amp; drynke it. Alſo take Nutmeg and ſmell to it, &amp; it wyll comforte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpyrytuall membres.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:36"/>
                  <head>¶Napo.</head>
                  <p>NApo this is named Nauew, it deſyreth grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that is fatty, and ſandy, it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth beſt in ſuche grounde, the properte of the Nauewe is, he chaungeth &amp; turneth in to rape and after that it turneth in to Nauewe, the beſt doth growe in grounde well dunged and tourned. Alſo it proueth well in places that ſtubble of corne hath ben in that ſame yere, yf they growe to thycke plucke ſome vp here and there, ſo that the other may proue the better, &amp; thoſe that ye plucke vp, ſet them in voyde pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. They ſhuld be ſowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ende of Iuly, and in Auguſt, the beſt ſauoured Nauewes be they that be longe and ſtrayghte, &amp; not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer great, nor braunches in the rotes, but a ſtrayght rote. Alſo of Nauewes may be made a paſſynge good mete with a lytel ſalt &amp; vyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre, ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and muſtarde, &amp; with ſwete ſpices, and it maye be made without ſpyces, Naue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes be hote in the ſeconde degre, and they no ryſſhe moche, but they be harde of degeſtyon, they make the fleſſhe ſofte &amp; wyndy, but leſſe wynde then rapes. Therfore when ye ſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in water, caſt that water away, and ſeth them in another water, and ſo his harde ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pred by that, &amp; ſo menely betwene good
<pb facs="tcp:3925:36"/>
and euyll they gendre noryſſhynge, for they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be thus well ſoden be not harde of degeſtion, they make one wyndy, &amp; they make ſtoppyng of vaynes and of poores, but yet they be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytable yf they be ſoden twyſe, and both the waters to be caſte away, and they to be ſoden in the thyrde water with fatte fleſſhe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="O" type="part">
               <head>¶The .xiii. letter begynneth with. O.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Olibanum.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Libanum is called Frankenſence, this is hote and dry in the thyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de degre, it is a gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of a tre in ynde, the cleneſt is the beſt. Alſo there be trees of that kynde gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng in Damaſke, but not ſo clere nor good for it is darker of coloure, therfore it is to be refuſed in medycyne. ¶The vertue is of com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fortynge by his ſwete ſauour. Alſo of cloſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and conſtraynynge,<note place="margin">Toth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ache.</note> for the tothache that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of ſuperfluyte of humours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hede, and ſpecyally by the vaynes, make a playſter of the powder of Frankenſence with wyne, &amp; the whyte of an egge, and medle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> togyther and playſter them aboute the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples. Alſo to
<pb facs="tcp:3925:37"/>
ſtop the wayes of the vaynes aboue, take Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenſence, and chewe it well in thy mouth, and that ſhall ſtop and let the fluxe of humours co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynge downe to the noſtryles,<note place="margin">to ſtop fluxe.</note> take pylles of Frankenſence, and ſwalowe them downe in the mornynge, than boyle Frankenſence in wyne, &amp; at euen drynke that whan thou goeſt to bed.<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> Alſo theſe pylles be good to helpe the degeſtyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſtomacke, and good agaynſt ſore balkynges. Alſo to the comfortynge and clenſynge of the matrice, and helpinge of con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepcion in the receyuinge the fume of Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenſence bindeth. Alſo boile powder of it in wyne, &amp; whan it is metely warme dyp a cloth in it, and laye it ſo warme to the ſhare of the pacient, &amp; greatly it comforteth the matryce.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="P" type="section">
               <head>¶The .xiiii. letter beginneth with. P.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Plumeus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes be colde &amp; moyſt ſome be white, and ſome be blacke, &amp; ſome be red. They that be blacke and ſomwhat harde be the beſt, they be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Damſons, &amp; whan they be ripe gather them, and ſlit them, &amp; ſpringe vinegre vpon them, and ſo they may be kepte
<pb facs="tcp:3925:37"/>
in a veſſell of woode a yeare and firſte whan they be cut they muſt be layde in the ſonne .xv dayes to dry. ¶The vertue of theſe Damſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haue coldnes &amp; clenſynge of the inwarde par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,<note place="margin">Feuer.</note> wherfore they be good in feuers that be ſharpe, &amp; for coſtyfnes of the bely that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of drynes, or of coloryke humours dryinge, yf it be newe gyue it hym to eate, yf it be drye boyle it in water, and gyue it the pacient to drinke therof,<note place="margin">Lyuer</note> this is good for the feuer terci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, for ſtoppinge of the liuer, for the Iau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and ſharp feuers, it ſofteth the bely,<note place="margin">Iau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> it is good for defaute of appetyte, and alſo for many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſeaſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Pyper.</head>
                  <p>PIper this is called Peper, it is hote and drye in the fourth degre. There be thre maner of Pepers, blacke, whyte, and longe Peper. Diaſcorides and Conſtantyne ſaye, that they be fruytes of trees growynge in yn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and ſome ſaye that Peper is made blacke with brennynge in the fyre, for whan it is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered there be great multytude of ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute it, and therfore they put it in the fyre, to brenne the ſerpentes that be aboute it, the Saraſyns dry it in an ouen, bycauſe it ſhall not encreaſe in another lande, but of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
<pb facs="tcp:3925:38"/>
the blacke is beſt, and the moſte holſome. ¶The vertue is, take Peper and put it in to thy noſe thrylles,<note place="margin">to neſe</note> and it wyll make the to neſe and ſeth Peper &amp; Fygges in wyne, &amp; drynke it,<note place="margin">Cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> and it wyll clenſe the ſpyrytuall membres of thoughe humours, &amp; it is good for the poſe that is taken of colde.<note place="margin">Poſe.</note> Alſo for the ſame eate powder of Peper with Figges. Alſo powder of Peper put in a mans meate comforteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> degeſtion of the ſtomacke.<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> Alſo put longe Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per in a roſted apple, and eate it, &amp; it ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte the degeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alſo powdre of Peper wyl frete away deed fleſſhe,<note place="margin">Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</note> or prowde fleſſhe, and longe Peper co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forteth more then blacke. Alſo blacke Peper hath vertue of loſynge, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge, and of drawynge, it clenſeth the ſpyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall membres of colde flewme,<note place="margin">fleume</note> and vycious humours, and beſt when the powder of it is eaten with Fygges, for he hath great ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght of hetynge &amp; comfortynge the ſtomacke,<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uokynge appetyte, but to ſanguyne and colo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryke perſones it is not good to vſe Peper, for it dryeth and brenneth bloude, &amp; it enge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth lepre, and other euyll ſyckenes. Pluto ſayeth, that Peper is fowle to ſe in ſyghte without blacke, &amp; within whyte, a ſharpe ſauoure and a ſwete odour, lytel i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyte, &amp; moch i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vertue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:38"/>
                  <head>¶Pympernell.</head>
                  <p>PImpernel is an herbe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> groweth in ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy places at the foote of the hylles. ¶The vertue is he is good for the fyſtula &amp; Canker,<note place="margin">Ka<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ker.</note> and he be puned and layde theron. Alſo it is good for dimnes of iyen, yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be waſhed with the water that it is ſoden in.<note place="margin">venym woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of this herbe dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll put away all venym from the body. Alſo this herbe is good to hele woundes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Pulegium.</head>
                  <p>POlegium is an herbe called Puliol royall it is hote and drye in the thyrde degre, in the tyme of flowerynge it ſhulde be gathered, and it may be kept in his vertue a yere, when it ſhal be vſed in medycines, take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leues with the flowers and ſtrype them from the ſtalkes. ¶The vertue is of loſynge &amp; conſumynge. For a colde humour in the heade,<note place="margin">Heade</note> take powder of it and hete it well in a ſkyllet, and all hote bynde it to the greuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce without any lycoure. Alſo for a great colde taken in the heade, and for a toughe humour or a watery humoure,<note place="margin">Humo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>urs.</note> make a gargaryſme, ſeth Pulyoll royall, and drye Fygges in tarte vynegre, &amp; take a good ſponfull therof as hote as ye maye ſuffre it, &amp; holde it in thy mouth tyll it be almoſte colde,
<pb facs="tcp:3925:39"/>
than put it out and take as moche more, and do ſo thre or foure tymes,<note place="margin">For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heade.</note> &amp; that ſhall ſpurge thy heed well of flewme. Alſo ſeth it in wyne and drynke it, &amp; it is good for the dyſeaſes in the ſtomacke in guttes,<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> and for colde cauſes, or for wynde in the ſtomacke. Alſo it is good for toughe flewme in the breſt, yf thou take powdre of it,<note place="margin">fleume</note> and medle it with claryfyde ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and make a lectuary therof, &amp; vſe to eate therof, or take the herbe therof &amp; boyle it with wyne, ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, or water, &amp; vſe to drynke therof. Alſo for the blacke colour drynke the ioyce of it,<note place="margin">colour</note> but boyle it with wyne, and thou ſhalte be hole.<note place="margin">Byle. ytchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</note> Alſo for an ytchynge byle, lay this herbe in water, and vſe to waſſhe the ytchynge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in warme, &amp; thou ſhalt be hole. Alſo for ache take this herbe al grene,<note place="margin">Ache.</note> and ſtampe it &amp; play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ache, &amp; it wyll eaſe it. Alſo agaynſt the coughe boyle this herbe in wyne,<note place="margin">coughe</note> &amp; drynke it luke warme, &amp; this wyl make one pyſſe wel. For the dyſeaſe in the bely,<note place="margin">Bely.</note> ſtampe this herbe with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn and water, &amp; lay it hote to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell,<note place="margin">Lyuer</note> &amp; lyghtly it ſhall be hole. For the dyſeaſe in the lyuer, ſtampe this herbe and tempre it with water and vynegre and drynke the ioyce therof and thou ſhalt be hole. For an ache in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> legges or armes, take the leues of elder &amp; Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyall
<pb facs="tcp:3925:39"/>
royall of eueryche alyke moche, &amp; ſtampe them togyther well and playſter it to the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and it is good for the feuer tercyan, yf thou take the braunches of this herbe, &amp; wrap it in a good locke of woll, and gyue it to the pacyent, &amp; let hym ſmell therto before the fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come on hym, and that ſhall do hym great eaſe. For the heedache,<note place="margin">heade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ache</note> take this herbe &amp; bynde it faſt rounde aboute thy heade, and anone it ſeaſeth the ache. Alſo yf a woman haue a deed chylde in her wombe, ſtampe this herbe,<note place="margin">a deed chylde</note> and gyue it her to drynke with olde wyne, and ſhe ſhall be delyuered of it thy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god. For the crampe drynke the ioyce with vynegre faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge, and it wyll put it awaye.<note place="margin">Cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Pencedanum vel Feniculus Porcinus.</head>
                  <p>PEncedanum, this herbe is called mayth hogges fenel, or mayden wede, this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be is hote and drye in the thyrde degre, when this herbe is gathered for medycynes, the rote is better then the herbe, when the rotes be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered they maye be kepte all a yeare.<note place="margin">ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lion. Flyxe. Lyuer.</note> ¶The vertue is he purgeth, it is good for the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulyon or the Flyxe, and good for ſtoppyng of the ſplen and the lyuer, boyle this herbe in wyne, or water, and gyue it to the pacyent to
<pb facs="tcp:3925:40"/>
drynke. Alſo ſeth it in oyle and wyne, &amp; play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter it to the ſhare, &amp; it wyl helpe the Strangu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flyxe. Alſo the ſame plaiſter is good for hardenes of the ſplen,<note place="margin">Splen Humo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>urs.</note> it molyfyeth that. Alſo agaynſt the colde humours of the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall membres, gyue hym to drynke water with barly, and this herbe ſoden togyther, and yf it be a feruent colde humour, then ſeth the barly and the herbe in wyne, and gyue it to the pacyent to drynke with lycoryce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Petrocilium.</head>
                  <p>PEtrocilium, this is called Perſley, this is hote &amp; moyſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrd degre. ¶The vertue is it multyplyeth greatly mans bloude and doth awaye the tyſyke.<note place="margin">bloude Tiſike Feuer. Harte. ſtomac</note> It helpeth well to dyſtroy the Feuer tertyan. It is good for the ſyde and the dropſye. It comforteth the herte and the ſtomacke. And it is good in potage, and to ſtoppe chekyns.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Peritorium.</head>
                  <p>PEritorium, this herbe is called Peritory and it is hote and drye. ¶The vertue of this herbe is thus, yf a man haue an euyll ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke or elles akynge within hym,<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> take this herbe and ſeth it in thy potage, and ete therof and thou ſhalt do well.<note place="margin">ſtone.</note> Alſo this herbe is good to hele one of the ſtone, yf he be bathed with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:40"/>
                  <head>¶Plaſtinaca.</head>
                  <p>PLaſtinaca, this is called a Peſnep, it is hote &amp; moyſte in the ſeconde degre, there be two maner of Paſneppes, the one is the Paſnep of the gardayne, and the other is the wylde Paſneppe, they be more vſed to meate than to medycyne. ¶ The vertue is to gendre thycke bloude &amp; moche,<note place="margin">bloude</note> wherfore it ſtyreth the luſt of the body yf it be moche vſed, therfore it is good for a man that is newly recouered out of his great ſyckenes to vſe to eate of it a whyle. Alſo they be good to be eaten rawe or ſoden for the melancoly humours grene and not drye.<note place="margin">Humo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>urs.</note> To make a ſyrope to ſtyrre the luſte of the bodye, and for to comforte the degeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take rotes of Paſneppes,<note place="margin">Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</note> and ſeth them well in water, than take them out and caſte awaye the water, and the rotes that be in gobettes boyle them agayne in water, than put therto ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny well claryfyed, and let them boyle vnto the thyckenes of ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually ſtyrre it that it cleue not to the veſſell and in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the boylynge, put in almondes yf ye haue them, &amp; in the ende of the boylynge put in Gynger, Galyngale, and a lytell Peper, Nutmege, and other ſwete ſauoured ſpyces. Alſo Paſneppes maye be ſowen in dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre, Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb facs="tcp:3925:41"/>
and Marche, in fat grounde &amp; depe dolue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and loſe grounde, and beſt dygged, and they be ſomwhat wyndy, boyle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in two waters, but caſt away the fyrſte water. Alſo there is a Paſnep that is ſomwhat red, the whiche may be eaten both rawe and ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and with them &amp; Nauewes togyther ye may make a very good meate, and fayre &amp; red in colour, the whiche be ſoden as Paſneppes be.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Plantago.</head>
                  <p>PLantago, this is called Playntayne, it is colde and drye in the ſeconde degre. ¶ The vertue is this, for hedache take Plantayne and bynde it aboute thy necke,<note place="margin">Heade</note> &amp; the ache ſhall go out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heed. Alſo for dyſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the body,<note place="margin">Body</note> ſeth this herbe in good lycoure in what ye wyll, and vſe to drynke it, &amp; it ſhall clenſe the mawe, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other inwardes. Alſo for hym that bledeth at the noſe,<note place="margin">bledi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</note> gyue hym to drynke the ioyce of it, &amp; it ſhall ſeaſe lyghtly. Alſo yf that the body of any man be wexen harde,<note place="margin">Body.</note> ſtampe this herbe with grece and make a playſter of it and lay it on the hardnes, and lyghtly it ſhall be ſofte and make it hole. Alſo for bytynge of a ſerpente,<note place="margin">biting.</note> take this herbe and drynke it with wyne. Alſo for the dyſeaſe in the mouth,<note place="margin">mouth</note> take the ioyce of this herbe, &amp; holde
<pb facs="tcp:3925:41"/>
it longe in thy mouth, &amp; eate the leues of this herbe. For hym that may not well pyſſe,<note place="margin">water.</note> ſethe this herbe and drynke it. Alſo for a rotten hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour in the breſt,<note place="margin">rotten humor</note> and aboute the herte take the ioyce of this herbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wayght of .x. <abbr>d</abbr>. and med<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le it with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and gyue hym to ete a ſpone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful at one tyme, and that ſhal ſpurge the breſt For ache i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fete, take this herbe with vynegre,<note place="margin">Ache.</note> and drynke it. Alſo it healeth woundes, and clenſeth the fylthe out of woundes. Alſo it ſwageth rankelynge, and ſtauncheth the men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions both with drynke &amp; with playſters ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de with powdre of Armonyake, &amp; of ſankdra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gone, &amp; barly mele, with the white of egges, made in a playſter, and layde to the ſore. For the canker and the payne in the gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, take,<note place="margin">Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ker.</note> the ioyce therof and medle it with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and vynegre, and powdre of Alume, and that ſhal ſlee the Canker in the mouthe. Alſo for the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſtamp thre rotes of Plantayne and tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pre it with water,<note place="margin">Feuer.</note> and gyue it hym to drynke that hath the Feuers, and he ſhal be hole. For the Iaundes ſtampe Plantayne and Letuſe togyther, and tempre them with vynegre,<note place="margin">Iau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> &amp; make a playſter therof and lay it to the ryght ſyde, and vſe it tyll thou be hole,<note place="margin">biting.</note> &amp; it is good for the bytynge of an adder, drynke the ioyce
<pb facs="tcp:3925:42"/>
of it, and lay the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the herbe to the ſore. For the ſame hange the rote of plantay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne aboute the necke of the pacyent, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylouſly it helpeth.<note place="margin">Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre.</note> For the potagre, and for the dyſeaſe in the ſynowes, ſtampe the leues of it with a lytel ſalt, &amp; playſter it well therto, and meruaylouſly it helpeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Porrum.</head>
                  <p>POrrum, this is called a Leke, it is hote &amp; drye in the thyrde degre, it deſyreth lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe grounde &amp; fat, &amp; well donged, in that they ſhall beſt profyte in hote places and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat, they maye be ſowen in Decembre in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat places, and colde. They may be ſowen in Ianuary. ¶The vertue is for a wounde, take Lekes and ſtampe them well with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny,<note place="margin">woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> and laye it to the wounde, and it wyll hele it. For the coughe take the ioyce of lekes and vſe to drynke it.<note place="margin">coughe</note> For the ſame, take the ioyce of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and medle it with womans mylke, &amp; vſe to drynke it, &amp; it wyl clenſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges of al vyce. ¶Fracturas ſolidat, duritaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> relaxat Vulnuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> appoſitum: cito cum ſale claudit.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Piretrum.</head>
                  <p>PIretrum, this is called Pelleter, it is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and drye in the thyrde degre, the rote is vſed in medycynes, fyue yeare he maye be
<pb facs="tcp:3925:42"/>
kept in his vertue, and knowe ye well that his ſharpnes is not knowen anone, it ſhuld be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and holden in the mouth. ¶The vertue is of loſynge, &amp; drawynge, &amp; of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumynge. To make a gargaryſme, take Pelleter &amp; Fyg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, &amp; boyle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vynegre or in ſwete wyne, and it wyll clenſe the brayne of ſuperfluyte of flewme. Alſo yf it be chewed in the mouth,<note place="margin">fleume</note> it helpeth the Palſy in the tongue.<note place="margin">Palſy. Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre.</note> Alſo for the palſy and the Potagre, ſtampe it &amp; ſethe it in wyne and oyle, &amp; playſter it to the greuaunce this playſter helpeth moche therfore, yf thou may haue grene pelyter ſtampe it, and lay it ſokynge in wyne .xv. dayes, and after boyle it wel and put therto wexe and oyle, for this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt oyntement for all the foreſayde dyſeaſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Papauer.</head>
                  <p>PApauer, this is called Popy, it is colde and dry. There is two maners of them, the whyte Popy is colde and moyſte, &amp; it is good to cauſe one to ſlepe, the ſede therof wel gathered may be kept .x. yeare. ¶The vertue is of clenſynge, it is put in medycynes with a determynacion as the ſede may be receyued of whyte Popy or blacke. For to prouoke a ſlepe, make a playſter of eche of them,<note place="margin">Slepe.</note> or one of them with womans mylke, and the whyte
<pb facs="tcp:3925:43"/>
of an egge, and laye it to the temples. The women of Salerne gaue to yonge chyldren the Popy, but they wolde gyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no blacke Popy, for it made them moche heuy. Alſo for a hote Poſtume in the begynnynge,<note place="margin">Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me. Lyuer</note> and for chafynge of the lyuer, take the ſede of whyte Popy, or els the herbe of it, and ſtamp it and medle it with oyle of Roſes, and plaiſter it to the greuaunce.<note place="margin">Feuer.</note> Alſo for drynes in feuer etyke and in other feuers, take &amp; hete oyle of vyolet medled with powder of Popy ſede, &amp; anoynt the ſmall of the backe therwith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Polipodium.</head>
                  <p>POlipodium, this is called Polipodye, it is hote in the thyrde degre, and drye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde degre. This polypody is a ferne that growe the vpon okes, or in walles, or ſtones, but the Polipody that groweth on Okes is the beſt, gather the rotes of it and lay it a day in the ſonne, choſe that is grene, &amp; that which appereth dry, when it is broken it is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed. ¶The vertue is of dyſſoluyng, of dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge,<note place="margin">fleume</note> of purgynge flewme, &amp; ſpecyally of mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>coly, wherfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly he is put in boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, &amp; to flewmatyke, &amp; melancolyous olde men, he is gyuen to preſerue theyr helth, and knowe wel that in the boylynge of Polypody
<pb facs="tcp:3925:43"/>
ſhulde be put in ſome thynge to exclude &amp; put out ventuoſyte as Anyſe ſede, Fenell ſede, for they exclude oute moche wynde,<note place="margin">Humo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>urs.</note> &amp; vnbyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth humours. Alſo for the cotydyan, and for Illica paſſio, &amp; to kepe a mans helth, do thus ſtampe halfe an ounce of Polipody or an ou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, yf ye wyl haue it moche laxatyue, than boy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le it with prunes and vyolettes in fenel water or anyſe, in a great quantyte, than ſtrayne it and gyue it the pacyente at euenynge and at mornynge. Alſo ſtamp it and ſeth it in water with fenel ſede, and make a good broth therof with a Chekyn therin, with ſwete ſauoured ſpyces, &amp; gyue the pacyent to eate. Alſo make a drynke therof after this maner, ſtampe it &amp; boyle it in wyne &amp; after put more wyne ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and ſo make vp your drynke with ſwete ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoured ſpyces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Pienium.</head>
                  <p>PIenium, this is called Pieny, it is hote and drye in the ſeconde degre, ſo ſayeth Ipocras and Galien the good Phyloſophers ſay that the rote therof goth to dyuers medy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynes, and it wyll laſt .x. yere, and it is colde. ¶The vertue is good for the Palſy,<note place="margin">Palſy.</note> drye the rote and drynke powdre with Caſter ſoden in wyne. Alſo the ſame is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone.<note place="margin">ſtone.</note> Alſo
<pb facs="tcp:3925:44"/>
yf a man be coſtyue &amp; may not go to draught take and ſtrawe the powdre therof on cotton,<note place="margin">coſtiue</note> and put in to his fundement, and drynke the powdre in whyte wyne. Alſo for a man or wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath the fallynge euyll,<note place="margin">Fali<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge euyll.</note> ete it &amp; drynke it in wyne. Alſo hange the rote aboute his necke, &amp; it wyll ſaue hym without doubt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in .xv. dayes. Alſo it helpeth the ſores in the mouth.<note place="margin">mouth</note> Alſo yf thou ſeth it in wyne it helpeth the ſplen. Alſo drynke Pyeny with water and ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and do therto powdre of Colyandre, &amp; this is good for the ſtomacke,<note place="margin">ſtomac Mylt.</note> for the mylte, &amp; for grauell in the raynes. Alſo it is good for wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for dyuers dyſeaſes, &amp; ſeth it in whyte wyne, and gyue a woman to drynke therof, &amp; it wyll hele her blader,<note place="margin">ſtone.</note> and make her to pyſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone, and it wyll hele her of the matrys. Alſo Pyeny ſede whan it is blacke, it maketh dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraunce of the bed of the chylde in her wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, and at euery tyme when ſhe ſhal vſe to drynke it, ſhe muſt drynke .xv. ſedes at one tyme.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Q" type="part">
               <head>¶The .xv. letter begynneth with. Q.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Quinquefolio.</head>
                  <p>QVinquefolio, this is called Qui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kefoyle, it is colde &amp; drye in the ſeconde degre, this herbe is good for ache in a mans
<pb facs="tcp:3925:44"/>
lymbes &amp; for ache of the heed, mouth, tongue,<note place="margin">Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes. Heade</note> and throte that is ſore, take &amp; ſethe this herbe in wyne, and gyue the pacyent to drynke ther of thre dayes fyrſte and laſt, &amp; he ſhall be hole. Alſo ſtampe it &amp; drynke the ioyce of it in ale, and it wyl ſeaſe the akynge &amp; gnawynge of a man or woman.<note place="margin">Gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge bledi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</note> Alſo yf a man blede ſore at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noſe gyue hym to drynke the ioyce of it with wyne, &amp; anoynt his heade well with the ioyce of this herbe, &amp; anone the bloude ſhall ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For to ſlee a canker,<note place="margin">Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ker.</note> ſethe it in wyne with the grece of a ſwyne, and make a playſter therof, and lay it on the Canker, &amp; it ſhal ſlee it. Alſo take powdre of Quynquefoyle, and medle it with honny, and therwith rubbe thy mouth, tongue, throte, and the chekes within, &amp; it wyl ſpurge it well.<note place="margin">Poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </note> Alſo for poyſon or bytynge of a ſerpent, take the ioyce of quynckefoyle, and drynke it with wyne, and meruaylouſly it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſteth venym.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="R" type="part">
               <head>¶The .xvi. letter begynneth with. R.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Rybbeworte.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ybbeworte is an herbe that groweth in gardaynes. ¶ The vertue is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feuer quartayne,<note place="margin">Feuer.</note> take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of this herbe, and drynke
<pb facs="tcp:3925:45"/>
it two houres before that ye thynke the dyſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſhall come to you, and by the grace of god it ſhall go fro you.<note place="margin">Eres.</note> For the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that here not well, put in to theyr eres the ioyce, and yf there be any rotten humours it wyll drye them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Rednetle.</head>
                  <p>REdnetle is called a palyfe of the grekes it is hote of vertue, for it bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth them that touche it. ¶The vertue is good for the Iaundes yf it be ſoden in wyne and dronke,<note place="margin">Iaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. cough.</note> it cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeth the colour meruaylouſly. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde coughe ſeth the ſedes in water, and put ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny therto, and drynke it, and it wyll hele y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cough, and take away the coldnes of the lunges, and ſwellynge of the bely. Alſo vynegre that the ſede of netels is ſoden in is good agaynſt ſcurfe in the heade,<note place="margin">Heade.</note> yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heade be waſſhed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with .ii. or .iii. tymes, and then rynſed with fayre water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Roſa.</head>
                  <p>ROſa, this is called red Roſe, it is colde in the fyrſt degre, and dry in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de degre, drye Roſes and grene roſes be vſed in medycynes, &amp; of grene Roſes be made many confectyons. Alſo drye roſes be put in medy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynes, when a receyte of Roſes is made, for they be ſone made i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> powdre, of roſes is made
<pb facs="tcp:3925:45"/>
mell roſet, ſugre roſet, ſyrop of roſes, alectua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Roſes, water of roſes, &amp; oyle of Roſes. Melroſet is made thus, take fayre puryfyed ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and newe red roſes, the whyte endes of them clyped away, then chop them ſmall, and put them in to the ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and boyle them mene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly togyther, to know whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is boyled ynough ye ſhall knowe it by the ſwete odour and the colour rufe, fyue yere he maye be kepte in his vertue. ¶The vertue of the roſes be of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortynge, and by the ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny he hath vertue of clenſynge.<note place="margin">Clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge.</note> In wynter and in ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer it may be gyuen compete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to feble, ſycke, flumatyke, melancolye, &amp; coloryke people. Alſo Mulſa is made of water and mele roſet, &amp; it may be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde day that it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bathe.<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> For to clenſe the ſtomacke of colde hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, gyue hym melroſet with water that fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel ſede is boyled in puttyng therin .iii. gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſalt, yf the ſycke may take it, this ſhuld be the quantyte of Roſes and ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny. In .vii. pounde of honny put a pounde of roſes. Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre roſet is made thus, take newe gathered ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, and ſtampe them ryght ſmall with ſugre, than put it in a glaſſe &amp; .xxx. dayes let it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in the ſonne, and ſtyrre it well &amp; medle it well togyther, &amp; ſo it may be kept thre yere in his
<pb facs="tcp:3925:46"/>
vertue. The quantyte of ſugre &amp; roſes ſhulde be thus in .iiii. pounde of Sugre a pounde of Roſes,<note place="margin">Fluxe.</note> he hath vertue of conſtraynynge, and comfortyng of the fluxe in the wombe, take ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre roſet &amp; powder of maſtyke, of euery one a dragma, and medle them well togyther and gyue it to the ſycke, after that gyue hym roſe water that Maſtyke and cloues be ſoden in. Syrop of Roſes is made thus, ſome do take Roſes dyght as it is beforeſayde, and boyle them in water, and i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that water ſtrayned they put ſugre and make a ſyrope therof, and ſome do make it better, for they put Roſes in a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell hauynge a ſtrayght mouth, and they put to the roſes hote water, and they let it ſtande a day and a nyght, &amp; of that water puttynge to it ſugre they make Syrope, and ſome do put more of Roſes in the forſayd veſſell, and more of hote water, and let it ſtande as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forſayde, and ſo they make a red water, and make therof a ſyrope, &amp; ſome do ſtampe newe Roſes, and they ſtrayne out the ioyce of it, &amp; ſugre therwith they make ſyrope, and this is the beſt makynge of Syrope, and knowe well that ſyrope made of freſſhe and newe Roſes, ſomwhat menely they be laxe, in the ende they bynde, but ſyrope made of drye roſes, fyrſte
<pb facs="tcp:3925:46"/>
and laſt they bynde. Syrope of Roſes hath vertue of comfortynge, and conſtraynyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the Fluxe of the wombe,<note place="margin">Fluxe.</note> &amp; he vomyte gyue it hym with rayne water, or with Roſe water in a feuer. After lettynge of bloude,<note place="margin">Blode</note> gyue it to hym with colde water. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame for the ſyncopyne.<note place="margin">ſynco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyne.</note> Oyle of Roſes is made this, ſome boyle roſes in oyle &amp; kepe it. Some do fyll a glaſſe with Roſes and oyle, and they boyle it in a caudren full of water, &amp; this oyle is good. Some ſtampe freſſhe roſes with oyle and they put it in a veſſell of glaſſe, and ſet it in the ſonne .l. dayes, and this oyle is good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt chafynge of the lyuer,<note place="margin">Lyuer</note> yf it be anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therwith. Alſo it is good for the dyſeaſe in the heade that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of hete,<note place="margin">Heade</note> anoynte the forheed, and the temples with oyle of Roſes, the water of roſes hath vertue of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortynge, and conſtraynynge agaynſt the fluxe of the wombe, and vomyte.<note place="margin">Fluxe.</note> Alſo gyue hym roſe wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter to drynke, or elles roſe water boyled with Maſtycke and cloues, it is beſte agaynſt the fluxe &amp; feblenes of vertue yf it come of a flux by a ſharpe medicine. Alſo roſe water is good for the ſyncopyne, and the Cardyacle,<note place="margin">cardya<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cle.</note> gyue it hym to drynke, and ſpryncle the water on his face, and the water is good for iyes, and
<pb facs="tcp:3925:47"/>
in oynteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes for the face, for it taketh away the wembes and the ſuperfluyte and ſtraineth the ſkynne. Alſo dry roſes put to the noſe to ſmell,<note place="margin">Harte.</note> do comforte the brayne, and herte, and quencheth the ſpyryte. Alſo agaynſt the fluxe of the wombe,<note place="margin">Fluxe.</note> &amp; colour, gyue hym roſes boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in rayne water. Alſo a playſter made of ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, and the whyte of egges and vynegre, and dyp a ſponge in it, and lay it on the mouth of thy ſtomacke,<note place="margin">Sinco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyne.</note> agaynſt the Syncopyne, gyue hym to drynke water that Roſes haue be boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in, and gyue hym powdre of roſes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a rere egge, to make oyle of roſes, take .ii. pounde of oyle, and a pounde and an halfe of roſes, and put all in a glaſſe, and put the glaſſe in a caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deron full of water, and hange it therin, and boyle it tyll the thyrde parte be waſted, &amp; after ſtrayne it throughe a lynen cloth, and kepe it for your vſe, for this oyle is loſynge, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for many thynges. Some do put Roſe water in a glaſſe, &amp; they put roſes with theyr dewe therto, and they make it to boile in water then they ſet it in the ſonne tyll it be red, and this water is beſt, this hath vertue of comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge, and conſtraynynge, and for the fluxe of the wombe, and agaynſt vomyte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Roſemarye.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3925:47"/>ROſemarye is an herbe that is hote and drye. ¶The vertue is good agaynſt al euylles in the body, take the flowers and put them in a lynnen cloth,<note place="margin">Body.</note> and ſo boyle them in fayre clene water to the halfe, and coole it and drynke it. Take the flowers and make powdre therof, &amp; bynde it to the ryght arme in a lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloth, and it ſhall make the lyght and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Alſo ete the flowers with honny faſtynge with ſowre breade, and there ſhall ryſe in the none euyll ſwellynges.<note place="margin">Swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge.</note> Alſo take the flowers and put them in a cheſt amonge your clothes or amonge bokes, and mothes ſhall not hurte them, boyle the flowers in gotes mylke, and than let them ſtande al a nyght vnder the ayre fayre couered, &amp; after that gyue hym to dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke therof that hath the Tyſyke, and it ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer hym. Boyle the leues in whyte wyne, &amp; waſſhe thy face therwith, thy herde, and thy browes, and there ſhall no cornes growe out, but thou ſhalt haue a fayre face, put the leues vnder thy beddes heed, and thou ſhalt be dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered of al euyl dremes. Breke the leues ſmal to powdre, and laye them on a Canker,<note place="margin">Dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ker.</note> and it ſhall ſlee it. Take the leues and put them in to a veſſell of wyne, and it ſhall preſerue it from tartnes and euyll ſauour, and yf thou ſell that
<pb facs="tcp:3925:48"/>
wyne, thou ſhall haue good lucke in the ſale. Yf thou be feble with vnkyndly ſwete, take &amp; boyle the leues in clene water,<note place="margin">Swet.</note> and whan the water is colde, do therto as moche of whyte wyne, and then make therin ſoppes, and eate well therof, and thou ſhalte recouer appetyte. Yf thou haue the fluxe, boyle the leues in ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ayſell, and bynde them in a lynen clothe, and than bynde it to thy wombe,<note place="margin">Fluxe.</note> and anone the fluxe ſhall withdrawe. Yf thy legges be blo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen with the goute,<note place="margin">goute.</note> boyle the leues in water, and then take the leues and bynde them in a lynen cloth about thy legges, and it ſhall do the good. Take the leues and boyle them in ſtronge Ayſell, and bynde them in a cloth to thy ſtomacke, and it ſhall delyuer the of all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyls.<note place="margin">ſtomac cough.</note> Yf thou haue the coughe, drynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water of the leues boyled in whyte wyne, and it wyl hele the. Take the rynde of Roſemary, and make powdre therof,<note place="margin">Poſe.</note> &amp; drynke it for the Poſe and it ſhall helpe the. Take the tymbre therof, and brene it to cooles, and make powdre ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and then put it in a lynen cloth and rubbe thy teth therwith, and yf there be any wormes therin it ſhal ſlee them,<note place="margin">Teth.</note> and kepe thy teth from all euyls. Alſo make the a boxe of the woode &amp; ſmel to it, and it ſhal preſerue thy youth. Alſo
<pb facs="tcp:3925:48"/>
put therof in thy dores, or in thy houſe, &amp; thou ſhalt be without daunger of adders and other venymous ſerpentes, make the a barell therof,<note place="margin">ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tꝭ</note> and drynke thou of the drynke that ſtandeth therin,<note place="margin">Poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </note> and thou nedes to fere no poiſon that ſhall hurte the. And yf thou ſet it in thy gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne, kepe it honeſtly, for it is moche profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Alſo yf a man haue loſt his ſmellyng of the ayre, or els he maye not drawe his breth,<note place="margin">Smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge.</note> make a fyre of the wood, &amp; take his breth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and gyue it hym to ete, &amp; he ſhall be hole.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Ruta.</head>
                  <p>RVta, this is called Rewe, this is hote &amp; dry in the ſeconde degre, the leues and the ſedes be vſed in medicynes, the ſedes may be kept .x. yeare, and the leues a yeare. ¶ The vertue is of purgynge, dyſſoluyng,<note place="margin">Heade.</note> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumynge. For the headache, take the ioyce of Rewe, and hete it &amp; put it in to his noſe thyrl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, for it ſpurgeth out flewme and clenſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brayne, the ioyce ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with wyne is good for the ſame. For feblenes of ſyght, put rewe in a pot with ale, and let the pacyent vſe to drynke of it. For ſtopynge of the ſplen and lyuer,<note place="margin">Eyes.</note> the ſtrangury and the fluxe, ſethe Rewe in wyne with rotes of Fenell, or powdre of rewe with the ioyce of Fenel and drynke it warme. Alſo
<pb facs="tcp:3925:49"/>
for an ache or fretyng,<note place="margin">Ache.</note> ſtampe rewe with pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn, and playſter it to the greuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Alſo agaynſt venym, drynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of rewe. For bytynge of a venymous beſte or worme,<note place="margin">Bytig</note> playſter rewe to the bytynge. For feble iye ſyght, ſtyll water of rewe and roſes togyther, &amp; put therof in your iyes.<note place="margin">Eyes.</note> Alſo an oyntment for ſore iyes, ſtampe rewe and fenell togyther of eche lyke moche by weyght, and medle them with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and Eufroſe, and it is a good oyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tement for ſore iyes. Take rewe, Comyn, &amp; Peper, of eche a lyke moche by weyght, and grynde them ſmall togyther, and medle them with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and vynegre,<note place="margin">Breſt.</note> and it is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ache in the breſt, and in the taynes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="S" type="part">
               <head>¶The .xvii. letter begynneth with. S.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Sinapium.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Inapium, it is called Muſtarde, it is hote and drye in the mydle of the .iiii. degre, &amp; not the herbe but the ſede is put in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycynes. Fyue yeare he may be kept i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his vertue. ¶ The vertue is of loſynge, of drawynge, of makynge thyn, and of conſumynge. For the
<pb facs="tcp:3925:49"/>
Palſye of the tongue,<note place="margin">Palſy.</note> take and chewe the ſede in your mouth, and holde it vnder the tongue and it ſhall do you good. Alſo for the palſy in other membres, ſeth the ſede in wyne,<note place="margin">me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres</note> and lay it to the ſore place, and it is beſt in the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the dyſeaſe. Alſo take the powdre of it, and put it in to your noſe thyrlles, and it wyll make you to neſe, and it clenſeth the brayne, and ſuperfluyte of flume.<note place="margin">Brain</note> Alſo ſeth it in wyne and fygges, and holde it warme in your mouth tyll it be almoſte colde, then take as moche more, &amp; do ſo .v. or .vi. tymes a day, and as moche another day, &amp; this is good for an olde poſe of toughe and flumy humour in the heed.<note place="margin">Poſe.</note> Alſo for ſtoppynge of the ſplen and the lyuer,<note place="margin">Heade Lyuer</note> ſeth the ſede in water with rotes of fenell, then ſtrayne it and put therto honny, and gyue it to the ſycke to drynke. For hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ſplen, ſeth the herbe of it in wyne,<note place="margin">Splen</note> and playſter it to the greuaunce. For to rype and breke a Poſtume,<note place="margin">Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</note> ſtampe this herbe well with hogges grece and laye it to the poſtume. Alſo for the ſtrangury, take this herbe, and ſeth it in oyle and wyne,<note place="margin">ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gury. Cyati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</note> and playſter it to the greuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and it wyll loſe it. Alſo for the Cia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyca, and for olde ſores, take muſtarde ſede, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde parte of cro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of whyte breade
<pb facs="tcp:3925:50"/>
and Fygges, ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and vynegre, after as the ache of the ſore requyreth, the more of the fyg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges and ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, that is there the more ſharper is the ſtrength of the ſede, and the more breade and vynegre that is in it, the more weker is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſede, but I ſaye not that ye ſhall put this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to al ſores, but to great and olde ſores his vertue is yf he be eaten, it ſharpeth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes wyt,<note place="margin">Bely. ſtone. ſtomac</note> it cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeth the bely, it breketh the ſtone it purgeth the vryne, menſtruoſyte, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth the ſtomacke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Smalage.</head>
                  <p>SMalage is an herbe that groweth in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daynes, it is hote and drye in the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the thyrde degre, &amp; drye in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the ſame. ¶ The vertue is good for col<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and wycked humours in the ſtomacke, and comforteth the ſtomacke,<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> the lyuer, and the lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and it is good for woundes, take Smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage ſede,<note place="margin">woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> rewe ſede, Peper, and ſalt, &amp; grynde them well togyther, and tempre them with wyne and drynke it. For ranklynges and to ceaſe the brennynge and akynge, &amp; to brynge them to theyr kynde agayne.<note place="margin">ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gꝭ Feuer.</note> Alſo it is good to drynke for the Feuer tercyan.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Saluia.</head>
                  <p>SAluia is called Sage, &amp; it is hote in the fyrſte degre, and dry in the ſeconde degre
<pb facs="tcp:3925:50"/>
the leues onely be taken in medycynes, both grene &amp; drye, he maye be kept a yeare. There be two maner of Sages, the gardayne and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wylde Sage, yf thou wylt haue ſage for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycynes, take the leues of gardayne Sage. ¶ The vertue is it conſumeth more, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forteth more then the other doth.<note place="margin">Palſy.</note> For the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy ſeth the leues of Sage in wyne, and vſe to drynke it, for the ſame ſeth the leues in wyne, &amp; playſter it to the greuaunce. Alſo it is good to put in ſauce, for the ſtrangury, the fluxe,<note place="margin">Fluxe. Clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge.</note> &amp; the matryce it clenſeth, ſeth the leues in water and let the pacyent ſyt ouer it, and receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hote fume of it, &amp; it ſhal do hym moche good. Alſo it is good for venym or poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">venym Poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </note> ſeth Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge in ale or wyne, &amp; vſe to drynke it .iii. daies, and thou ſhal be hole by the grace of god. For the ſtomacke drynke the ioyce of Sage with water and ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, &amp; it is good to clenſe a mans body to vſe it both rype &amp; grene, it wyll make a mannes body clene,<note place="margin">Body.</note> therfore who that vſeth to eate of this herbe or drynke it, it is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle that any inconuenyence ſhulde greue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that vſe it.<note place="margin">ychi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge.</note> Yf ye haue an ytchynge on you waſſhe it well with the ioyce of this herbe, and it ſhall ſlee the ytchynge. Alſo drynke Sage with wyne, &amp; a lytell wormwode, and it ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:3925:51"/>
ceaſe the ache vnder the ſydes,<note place="margin">ſtomac Palſy. dropſy</note> the wombe, &amp; the ſtomacke, it is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> palſy &amp; dropſy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Satureia.</head>
                  <p>SAtureia is called Sauery, it is hote and drye in the .iiii. degree. ¶ The vertue of this is,<note place="margin">Body. raynes</note> it purgeth the body, ſeth it in wyne or water &amp; drynke it, and it purgeth the raynes, the bladder, the menſtruoſyte in the bowels, it purgeth the lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges &amp; loſeth great humours,<note place="margin">Lungꝭ</note> and conpelleth and putteth hym oute by the mouth by ſpyttynge, therfore he is bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge and ſtyreth hym that vſeth lechery, therfore it is forbyd to vſe it moche in meates. Soke it in vynegre or wyne, and drynke it, &amp; it ſhall make the haue a meke ſtomacke.<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> Alſo when it flowreth, it ſhulde be gathered and dryed, and powdre made therof. Alſo take the powdre of Sauery, and boyle it with claryfyed honny, and vſe to ete therof, or boyle it in wyne, and drynke it,<note place="margin">fleume Fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge.</note> and it wyll loſe toughe flewme in the breſt. Alſo for frettinge in the bely drynke powdre of it in warme wyne, and thou ſhall be hole. Alſo yf ye take the leſſe Sauery, it hath the ſame vertue and ſtrength that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sauery hath. Alſo make grewel with wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter and flower,<note place="margin">me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres</note> and powdre of Sauery, and eate therof and that ſhall clenſe all the ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb facs="tcp:3925:51"/>
membres of a man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Saxfrage.</head>
                  <p>SAxfrage is hote and drye in the thyrde de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre. ¶ The vertue is good for the ſtone,<note place="margin">ſtone.</note> ſeth the ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of it in wyne, and drynke it. Alſo it is good for the dyſeaſe of Colyke and the ſtrangury, and the powdre of it be eaten with an egge, it is good for the ſame.<note place="margin">Colike</note> It maye be kept in his vertue .iii. yeare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Scabioſa.</head>
                  <p>SCabioſa is called Scabias, it is hote &amp; drye in the thyrde degre, to dry it there is no profyte in it. ¶ The vertue is good for the ſcabbes, take the ioyce of it, vynegre, &amp; oyle,<note place="margin">ſcabs.</note> and boyle them togyther tyll they wax thycke and kepe it, for it is good for ſcabbes. For the Emerawdes ſeth them in water,<note place="margin">Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raudes</note> then ſyt ouer it, and take the fume of it and vſe it, and thou ſhall be hole. Stampe it and ſeth it in wyne, and the drynke is good to dyſtroye humours in the ſtomacke, and drynke it euery daye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge with Euroſe, and thou ſhall be hole, and thou ſhalt neuer haue the Peſtylence bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng within the whyle thou do vſe it.<note place="margin">Peſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</note> For the lyuer ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe it and ſeth it in wyne, &amp; drynke it</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Sothernwood.</head>
                  <p>SOthernwode is an herbe that groweth in
<pb facs="tcp:3925:52"/>
the felde. ¶The vertue of it is good for the coughe,<note place="margin">cough. Bely. Breſt.</note> and for byndynge in the bely, and in the breſt, and for dyſeaſe in the bones, &amp; good for them that maye not wel pyſſe, take the ſede of this herbe and ſtamp it, and drynke it with water, and it is good for all the aforeſayde. Alſo for the dyſeaſes in the ſyde, ſtampe this herbe with byttayne and drynke it,<note place="margin">Syde. Byti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> and it hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth well. Alſo for the bytynge of a ſerpent, &amp; for venym, ſtampe this herbe and drynke it with wyne, and it is good. Alſo for the colde feuer,<note place="margin">Feuer.</note> ſtampe this herbe with wyne, &amp; drynke it, and thou ſhall be hole.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Syngrene.</head>
                  <p>SIngrene. is colde and moyſte in the .iii. degre. ¶ The vertue of this herbe, &amp; alſo the ioyce of the ſame herbe is neceſſary for ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny dyſeaſes, ſtampe this herbe with grece and playſter it to the dyſeaſe and meruaylouſly it helpeth. For dyſeaſes &amp; darkenes of the iyes, ſtampe this herbe and put of the ioyce in the ſore iyes.<note place="margin">Eyes. Lyuer</note> For chafynge of the lyuer, take the ioyce of it and vynegre, and dyp a cloth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and playſter it to the greuaunce. For by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge or ſcaldyng,<note place="margin">Biti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> make an oyntment of the ioyce of this herbe, and oyle of roſes &amp; waxe, but lay it not to tyl after the thre fyrſt dayes,
<pb facs="tcp:3925:52"/>
but fyrſte anoynt it with grece &amp; ſuche other. Alſo for a dyſeaſe of a hote cauſe, this is good to be layde therto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Stytcheworte.</head>
                  <p>STytchewort or byrdeſtonge,<note place="margin">ſtytche woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Eyes.</note> this is hote and moyſte in the fyrſt degre. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of this herbe is this, it is good to hele ſtyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, woundes, and alſo ſore iyes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Scamony.</head>
                  <p>SCamony is hote and drye in the .iii. de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre, the leues onely be beſt in medy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynes, it may be kept a yere in his ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue or two for nede. ¶ The vertue is good for the dyſeaſe in the ſtomacke,<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> boyle the leues of it in wyne, and drynke it. Alſo the aforeſayde drynke is good for the bely.<note place="margin">ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Fluxe.</note> For the ſtrangu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and flux, alſo a ſtewe made with boylynge of it in water or wyne, is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſayd yf it be boyled in oyle, and playſter it to the ſame aforeſayd, it is better.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Sene.</head>
                  <p>SEne is hote and drye in the .iiii. degre it groweth on the other ſyde the ſee, &amp; moſte aboute Babylon, the beſt be the flowers and the braunches of it.<note place="margin">Falli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g euyll. ſplen.</note> ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is good for many dyſeaſes, as the fallyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge euyll, for the ſyncop, for the ſplen, for the
<pb facs="tcp:3925:53"/>
Emerawdes,<note place="margin">Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne.</note> and for the quartayne, ſyrope made of it boyled in water, and ſugre is good for all the aforſayd, ſyrope made with the ioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of Borage is good for the aforſayde. Alſo Dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcorydes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth to make Exmell of the aforeſayde with boylynge of vynegre &amp; ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and it wyll be good for the aforeſayde. And this herbe may be kepte .x. yeare in his ſtrength and vertue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Selondyne.</head>
                  <p>SElondyne is hote and drye in the .iiii. degre, and Galyen ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is good for ſore iyes. ¶ The vertue is good for ſore iyes, take the ioyce of ſelondyne, and the rote boyle it wel togyther in a panne,<note place="margin">Eyes.</note> and when it is colde anoynte thy iyes therwith. Take ſelondyne and wrynge oute the ioyce,<note place="margin">Frak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyſage</note> and medle it with whyte wyne, and anoynte thy vyſage therwith, and it ſhall do away frak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les of the vyſage. The ioyce of ſelo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyne and gotes donge medled togyther ſmall in a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ker.</note> then yf thou laye it to a Canker in a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans pappe, it ſhall ſlee the canker. Alſo take the ioyce of Selondyne,<note place="margin">Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fewe.</note> &amp; powdre of brym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and medle them well togyther, &amp; it wyll helpe to do awaye the morfewe, and ſethe the rote in wyne, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pot is taken downe
<pb facs="tcp:3925:53"/>
let hym holde his mouth open ouer it, that the breth may go in to his body, and that ſhall ſlee the Canker in the mouth,<note place="margin">Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ker. venym</note> it is good for hym that hath dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken venym with his owne ſtale, and that wyll ſaue hym.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Sauayne.</head>
                  <p>SAuayne is hote and dry in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de degre.<note place="margin">wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> ¶ The vertue is good to ſlee wormes in the wombe, and to brynge them out yf it be ſoden in wyne, and gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the pacyent to drynke. It is good with butter or grece to make an oyntment for the ſcabbe that re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth to hele it and drye it vp,<note place="margin">Scab. Heade ache.</note> and it is good for the hedache, yf it be ſtamped and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. pered with vynegre, and make a playſter ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and laye it to thy temples and vpon the molde of thy heade.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Scabioſe.</head>
                  <p>SCabioſe is colde and moyſte in the .ii. degre.<note place="margin">Lyuer.</note> ¶ The vertue of this herbe is good for the lyuer, ſtampe it and ſeth it in wyne.<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> And it wyll dyſtroye wycked hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours in the ſtomacke, &amp; drynke it euery day faſtynge with Euroſe,<note place="margin">Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</note> and thou ſhall neuer haue poſtume bredynge within the, as longe as thou doſte vſe this medycyne.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="T" type="part">
               <head>¶ The .xviii. lettre begynneth with. T.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:54"/>
                  <head>¶ Townecreſſes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ownecreſſes, is hote and drye in the thyrde degre, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de wyll endure good .v. yeare. ¶ The vertue is good to ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the flux and the menſyon,<note place="margin">Fluxe. Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </note> yf thou take the ſede and broyſe it in a morter of braſſe, and gyue the ſycke to drynke therof thre dayes euery daye a peny wayght at ones with red wyne warmed, and in theſe .iii. daies he ſhall be ſtaunched, or els he ſhall dye of that euyll,<note place="margin">Palſy. Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke.</note> it is good for the palſy, and for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leflanke, take the ſede and ſeth it with wyne &amp; do it in a pocket, &amp; bynde it to the ſyde there as the greuaunce is. Alſo it is good for hym that maye not pyſſe,<note place="margin">water.</note> take the ſede and ſeth it in wyne and oyle Olyue, &amp; bynde it to thy ſhare.<note place="margin">Fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> It is good for a mans fundament that goeth out, yf it be taken of colde, then it muſt be put in agayne, &amp; ſtrawe the powdre on the foundement, thy raynes with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, &amp; then ſtrawe the powdre aboue with the powdre of Comen, or powdre of Calafyne, for all theſe be kyndly for it. Alſo take the ſtalkes of Tow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>necreſſes, &amp; bren them, &amp; there ſhall no veny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous beeſt, ne worme abyde the ſauour nor ſmell therof, but he ſhal dye or els flye away.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:54"/>
                  <head>¶ Tapſuberbeſto.</head>
                  <p>TApſuberbeſto is called Melon, it is col<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and drye. ¶ The vertue of it is good for the Emerawdes,<note place="margin">Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rawdꝭ.</note> and it be ſoden in wyne and ſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med clene. Alſo it is good to waſſhe the greuaunce therwith. It is good alſo for the fluxe in the belye. To prouoke vomyte, take two dragmes of the powdre of the rote of Melon, and drynke it in wyne,<note place="margin">Fluxe.</note> and it wyl prouoke vomyte.<note place="margin">vomite water. ſtone.</note> Alſo the ſedes prouoketh vryne and cauſeth the to pyſſe, and clenſeth, the raynes &amp; the bladder of grauell &amp; ſtones.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="V" type="part">
               <head>¶ The .xix. letter begynneth with. V.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶Vyolet.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Yolet is colde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte degre, and moyſte in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde. ¶ The vertue of it is good for a blaſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iyes take the rotes of vyolettes,<note place="margin">Eies.</note> and ſtampe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with myrre and ſaffron, &amp; at nyght lay it to the ſore iyes Alſo for a wounde in the heade,<note place="margin">wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dꝭ.</note> ſtamp the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of vyolettes with honny and vynegre, &amp; playſter it to the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, &amp; it ſhall hele it. Alſo for them that may not ſlepe for ſyckenes ſethe this herbe in water,<note place="margin">Slepe</note> and at euen let hym ſoke
<pb facs="tcp:3925:55"/>
well his fete in the water to the ancles, when he goth to bed, bynde of this herbe to his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,<note place="margin">Slepe</note> and he ſhall ſlepe well by the grace of God. Take Vyolettes Myrre, and Saffron and make a playſter,<note place="margin">Eies.</note> &amp; laye it to the ſore iyes that be ſwolen, &amp; it ſhall ceaſe akynge, &amp; bate the ſwellynge</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Vua ſuauis.</head>
                  <p>VVa ſuauis, this is called the ſwete ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyn, it is hote and moyſte. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is of clenſynge, ſcowryng, or ſmothynge Rayſynges eaten or boyled in wyne is good for the colde coughe.<note place="margin">cough. Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me. ſtomac</note> Alſo ſeth them in wyne and they be good to playſter on the colde po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume, &amp; alſo good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> colde ſtomacke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Veruayne.</head>
                  <p>VEruayne, this is hote and drye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde degre. ¶ The vertue is good for all maner of euylles of venym,<note place="margin">venym</note> yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pacyent drynke it tempred with wyne, and ſtamp the herbe,<note place="margin">Byti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> &amp; laye it on euery maner of bytynge of venymous beeſt, &amp; it wyll drawe out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> venym &amp; ſaue the ſore, who that vſeth it, it wyll make good breth,<note place="margin">Breth</note> &amp; do away the ſtynke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth Alſo who that hath the Feuer tercyan, take .iii rotes and .iii. croppes of the ſame herbe and,<note place="margin">Feuer</note> ſtamp them and tempre them with fayre clene
<pb facs="tcp:3925:55"/>
water, and gyue it to the pacient to drynke. Alſo who that hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feuer quartayn,<note place="margin">Feuer</note> let hym take the ſame drynke. Alſo it is good for the ſtomacke, the lyuer, and the lunges.<note place="margin">ſtomac Lyuer</note> Alſo take Veruayne, Betayne, and Saxfrage, of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them a lyke moch, and ſtamp them with whyte wyne tempred,<note place="margin">ſtone.</note> &amp; this is good for them that hath the ſtone. Alſo they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bere Veruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vpon them,<note place="margin">Loue.</note> they ſhall haue loue &amp; grace of great mayſters, &amp; they ſhall alſo graunte hym his aſkynge, yf that his aſkyng be good and ryghtfull, this herbe is hote &amp; drye.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="W" type="part">
               <head>¶ The .xx. lettre begynneth with. w.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ watercreſſes</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Atercreſſes be hote and drye in the ſeconde degre. ¶ The vertue of this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be is good yf ye ſethe them in water by them ſelfe,<note place="margin">Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres. ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lion. Fluxe.</note> and drynke it, or ſeth it i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fleſſhe and ſup of the broth, and it wyll clenſe well the inwarde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres. Alſo it is good agaynſt the ſtrangulyon and the fluxe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ wylde neppe or wodbynde.</head>
                  <p>wYlde neppe or woodbynde, this herbe be reth a flower lyke to the hop, &amp; after the flower he bereth a grene bery, &amp; it hath
<pb facs="tcp:3925:56"/>
a great roote. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is moſte in the rote, it is good for ſynowes that be ſhronken,<note place="margin">Syno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes.</note> or cut to make them ſouple, and to haue theyr owne courſe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr propre kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Go to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rote of wylde Neppe, that is lyke woodbynde, &amp; make a hole in the myddes of the rote, then couer it well agayn y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ayer, go out nor y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no rayne go in nor water, pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre, nor the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne come not to moche to it, let it ſtande ſo all a nyght and a daye, then after that go to it, and thou ſhalt fynde therin a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne lycour, take out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> licour with a ſpone, and put it in to a clene glaſſe, &amp; do ſo euery day as longe as thou fyndeſt ought in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole and this muſt be done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moneth of Apryl, or May, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anoynt the ſore with it agaynſt the fyre, then wete a lynen clothe in the ſame lycour, and lap it aboute the ſores and it ſhal be hole in ſhorte ſpace on warantyſe, by the grace of god.<note place="margin">gowte.</note> For the gowte a ſouerayne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycyne, take the rote of wylde Nep, &amp; the rot of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wylde docke ſoden by it ſelfe, &amp; cut them in thyn peces, and pare awaye the vtter rynd and cutte them in quarters, then boyle them in clene water .ii. or .iii. houres, then ſtampe them in a morter as ſmall as can be, then put therto a quantyte of ſote of a chymny, &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pre
<pb facs="tcp:3925:56"/>
them with the mylke of a kowe that the he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re is of one colour, then take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pyſſe of a man that is faſtyng, &amp; make a playſter therof, and boyle it togyther, and as hote as ye maye ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fre it, laye it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greuaunce a day &amp; a nyght &amp; ſo do .ix. tymes &amp; it ſhall hele the on waran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe by the grace of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ wormwood.</head>
                  <p>WOrmwood is hote and drye in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde degre. ¶ The vertue is good for wormes in the wombe,<note place="margin">wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> yf it be ſtamped and the ioyce wrong out, and myngled with ſwete mylke, and gyue to the pacye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, and ſeth this berbe in wyne, and make a playſter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wombe, make powdre of worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Centory betayne, of eche a lyke moch by wayght, and medle all well togyther, and the powdre wyl ſlee wormes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wombe both when it is eaten in potage and dronken.<note place="margin">wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be.</note> Alſo for the mylte that is ſwollen of a colde mater ſeth it in wyne and let the ſycke drynke therof and that ſhal hele hym,<note place="margin">Mylt.</note> and make a playſter of the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the herbe, and lay it all hot to thy wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be agaynſt the greuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Alſo ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, wormwood &amp; tempre it with vynegre, and with toſted ſowre bread grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den therwith &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of myntes, and the ioyce of plantayne
<pb facs="tcp:3925:57"/>
of eche a lyke moche, and frye them wel togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then make a playſter and laye it to the mouth of the ſtomacke,<note place="margin">ſtomac</note> &amp; this ſhall ſtaunche, brekynge or caſtyng, For wormes in a mans eres be it ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or erewygge,<note place="margin">wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy.</note> take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of wormwood, and put it in the ere. Alſo for the dropſy ſeth it in wyne, &amp; gyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſycke to drin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke at mornyng and at euenynge, and it ſhall helpe hym.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Hereafter foloweth the vertue of the Oken tree.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Oke be .iiij. thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges beſyde the lefe the which be ryght profytable to the, helth of a man, that is to wyt the Acorne, and the cup that it groweth in, the galles and the lyme. The carnels in powdre be profyta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble agaynſt the feblenes of vertiuer of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentyfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay agaynſt feblenes of bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and agaynſt the paſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> called diabetican,<note place="margin">Brain ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye. ſtone.</note> and agaynſt the ſtrangurye, and agaynſt the ſyckenes called diſſenturian, and agaynſt the ſtone in the raynes, and the bladder, and it is
<pb facs="tcp:3925:57"/>
good for them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may not holde theyr water.<note place="margin">water. vomite</note> The cuppe of the A cornes is good agaynſt vomytes of colour, and agaynſt neſyng, and it dryeth,<note place="margin">Neſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. ſtomac</note> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumeth flewme in the mouth of the ſtomacke. The gall after the opynion of Albert, ſo that they be not greatly holowe be good agaynſt the fluxe, and agaynſt ſlydyng and ſlypernes of guttes,<note place="margin">Fluxe.</note> &amp; agaynſt the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of women, and that powdre helpeth them of many infyrmyties. &amp;c. ¶ Alſo by experyen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of Gardyners, and planters, the powdre of the gall mynged with honny, perce a hole in a tre, &amp; put it therin, &amp; the fruyte ſhal be blacke. Nowe with the lyme of the Oke, Phyſycio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and Surgyans do many cures therwith, and of it is made an oyntment for the palſy, and of a mans yarde,<note place="margin">Palſy.</note> and agaynſt an infyrmyte called Deabetan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alſo therof is made ſayrope for the Dropſy that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of colde called y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſarco, and it conſumeth watery humours.<note place="margin">Debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> And alſo men be cured by the fruyte of ares quartayne, tercian, and cotydyan.<note place="margin">Terci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Cotidi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an.</note> Alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tre is a thynge growyng, which wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowe by experyence it maketh them haſtely to be de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuered of chylde, whiche dowche men call it Archemſel, and therof is made bedes. ¶The laſt concluſyon of this Oken leues, of this le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues
<pb facs="tcp:3925:58"/>
is diſtylled a water,<note place="margin">Fluxe. wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raudes bledi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. Lyuer. Splen Neſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. cough. Heade ache. ſtomac</note> whiche healeth all the Fluxe of the wombe called Dyſſentuaryan, Lauaryan, and Dyaryan. Alſo it is good for the flowers of women, and for the Emeraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Alſo this lefe in powdre put in the noſe, ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheth the bledynge therof, and ſpyttynge of bloude. Alſo this lefe is holſome agaynſte the ache of the herte, agaynſt the epilacion of the lyuer, and of the ſplen, &amp; agaynſt the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge, and agaynſt the coughe, and the heade ache, and agaynſt the ache of the ſtomacke, &amp; the wynde of the ſtomacke, &amp; agaynſt the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke, and the ache of the wombe, and the flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes,<note place="margin">ſtone.</note> and it breketh the ſtone of the raynes, &amp; the bladder, and alſo women that be colde, it dyſpoſeth them to be able to conceyue, it is holſome to all maner of creatures of all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ages, and for all dyſeaſes to be taken at al tymes of the yere. &amp;c. ¶wherfore Surgyans knowynge the trouth leyth Oken leues vpon wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and that done they nede none other oyntment,<note place="margin">woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ker. Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy.</note> it heleth all maner of woundes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Canker, the Fyſtula, &amp; ſaynt Anthonies fyre a vayne made in the water of the Oke heleth the Dropſy, and all lepourneſſe. Alſo who ſo euer ones in the weke eateth one of the leues, he ſhall neuer haue ſtynkynge breth, nor the
<pb facs="tcp:3925:58"/>
toth ache, nor putrefaction in his gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes.<note place="margin">Toth ache. Eares.</note> &amp;c. nor of his eares.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶This is the makynge of Aqua vite perfectiſſima.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake the rote of Saxfrage, &amp; Parcely, Alyſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre, Fenel, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, Yſope, Pynyryall, Roſemary Laue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, Prymeroſe, Mynt Ori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gan, Sauge, Calamynt, Auence, Byttayn Saueyn, of eche halfe a quartron, Galynga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, blacke Peper, whyte Peper, longe Peper, Cloues, Nutmegges, of eche an ounce, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, Maces, Quybybes, of eche two ounces, Setwale, Pelettre of ſpayne, tre of Aloes, of eche an ounce and an halfe, and ſtampe thyne herbes, and powdre thy ſpyces, &amp; put them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther in the wyne, &amp; let them ſtande al nyght and on the morowe dyſtyll them throughe a ſerpentory, this water hath many vertues, &amp; it is better at the fyrſt dyſtyllacion of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, then at the thyrde dyſtyllacion of the Serpentorye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶To graffe and plante.</head>
               <p>TO graffe fruyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall haue no core. Take a graffe and bowe it in both endes combynge, and cutte both endes graftwyſe, and ſo faſten them in to the ſtocke.
<pb facs="tcp:3925:59"/>
And yf it growe ſo with the tre cutte awaye the great ende, and let the ſmaller ende growe and his fruyte ſhall haue no core.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶Thus endeth this Herball.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>¶Here begynneth the table of this preſent boke.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>¶Agnus caſtus.</item>
               <item>Apium.</item>
               <item>Anetum.</item>
               <item>Apium riſus.</item>
               <item>Abſynthium.</item>
               <item>Artemeſia.</item>
               <item>Affodyllus.</item>
               <item>Aſtrologia longa.</item>
               <item>Aſtrologia rotunda.</item>
               <item>Abrotanum.</item>
               <item>Ameos.</item>
               <item>Alleluya.</item>
               <item>Agrimonia.</item>
               <item>Auancia.</item>
               <item>Altea.</item>
               <item>Amariſta.</item>
               <item>Aniſum.</item>
               <item>Alleum.</item>
               <item>Aſtarton.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>¶Betonia.</item>
               <item>Balſaminta.</item>
               <item>Beta.</item>
               <item>Borago domeſtices.</item>
               <item>Bigula.</item>
               <item>Burneta.</item>
               <item>Burſa paſtoris.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>¶Camamilla.</item>
               <item>Callamyntum.</item>
               <item>Craſſula maior.</item>
               <item>Craſſula minor.</item>
               <item>Cituca.</item>
               <item>Centuaria maior.</item>
               <item>Centuaria minor.</item>
               <item>Carin.</item>
               <item>Celodonia.</item>
               <item>Cidamum.</item>
               <item>Canlis.</item>
               <item>Coriandrum.</item>
               <item>Capillus veneris.</item>
               <item>Crocus.</item>
               <item>Centinodium.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:59"/>Caprifolium.</item>
               <item>Canabaria.</item>
               <item>Coſtus.</item>
               <item>Cepe.</item>
               <item>Columbina.</item>
               <item>Cominum.</item>
               <item>Cardiaca.</item>
               <item>Ciſera.</item>
               <item>Camelion.</item>
               <item>Conſolida maior.</item>
               <item>Conſolida minor.</item>
               <item>Conſolida media.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>Dragancia.</item>
               <item>Diptanum.</item>
               <item>Daucus aſinius.</item>
               <item>Dancus creticus.</item>
               <item>Dens leonis.</item>
               <item>Dragancia feminea.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>¶Elena campana.</item>
               <item>Endiua.</item>
               <item>Eruca.</item>
               <item>Eufragia.</item>
               <item>Ebulus.</item>
               <item>Edera.</item>
               <item>Edera tereſtris.</item>
               <item>Eborus.</item>
               <item>Elabrus.</item>
               <item>Epatica.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>¶Famula.</item>
               <item>Fumus terre.</item>
               <item>Fragra.</item>
               <item>Fabaria maior.</item>
               <item>Filex.</item>
               <item>Filipendula.</item>
               <item>Feniculum.</item>
               <item>Faxmus.</item>
               <item>Finiculus porcinus.</item>
               <item>Febrifuga.</item>
               <item>Filago.</item>
               <item>Flamula minor.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>¶Granum.</item>
               <item>Geneſcula.</item>
               <item>Genciana.</item>
               <item>Galanga.</item>
               <item>Granum ſolis.</item>
               <item>Gladiolus.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:60"/>Gracia dei.</item>
               <item>Gracia dei maior.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>¶Haſtula regia.</item>
               <item>Herba cruciata.</item>
               <item>Herba chriſtfori.</item>
               <item>Herba walteri.</item>
               <item>Herba Roberti.</item>
               <item>Herba martis.</item>
               <item>Herba Iohannis.</item>
               <item>Herba Petri.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>¶Iuſquiamus.</item>
               <item>Iſopus.</item>
               <item>Ireoſe.</item>
               <item>Iris.</item>
               <item>Iua.</item>
               <item>Iacia alba.</item>
               <item>Iacia nigra.</item>
               <item>Ippia maior.</item>
               <item>Ippia minor.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>¶Laniſticum.</item>
               <item>Lingua ceruina.</item>
               <item>Lilium.</item>
               <item>Liguſtrum.</item>
               <item>Lingua bouis.</item>
               <item>Lingua ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tisma.</item>
               <item>Lingua Serpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tismi.</item>
               <item>Lingua canis.</item>
               <item>Lingua hircina.</item>
               <item>Lupinus.</item>
               <item>Labrum veneris</item>
               <item>Lauendula.</item>
               <item>Lactuca.</item>
               <item>Lactuca ſiluatica.</item>
               <item>Lactuca leporica.</item>
               <item>Lollium.</item>
               <item>Laparium rubeum.</item>
               <item>Linum.</item>
               <item>Lauriola.</item>
               <item>Licoriſa.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>¶Millefolio minor.</item>
               <item>Mercurialis.</item>
               <item>Menta.</item>
               <item>Menta romana.</item>
               <item>Malua.</item>
               <item>Morell or nyght ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe.</item>
               <item>Maſtyke.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:60"/>Magerum.</item>
               <item>Millefolium maior.</item>
               <item>Motherworte, or</item>
               <item>Mugworte.</item>
               <item>Maces.</item>
               <item>Menta.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>¶Nux muſcata.</item>
               <item>Napo.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>¶Olibanun.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>¶Plumeus.</item>
               <item>Piper.</item>
               <item>Pympernell.</item>
               <item>Pulegium.</item>
               <item>Pencedamum vel Fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niculus porcinus.</item>
               <item>Petrocilium.</item>
               <item>Peritorium.</item>
               <item>Plaſtinaca.</item>
               <item>Plantago.</item>
               <item>Porrum.</item>
               <item>Piretrum</item>
               <item>Papauer.</item>
               <item>Polipodium.</item>
               <item>Pienium.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q</head>
               <item>¶Quinquefolio.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>¶Rybbeworte.</item>
               <item>Rednetell.</item>
               <item>Roſa.</item>
               <item>Roſemary.</item>
               <item>Ruta.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>¶Sinapium.</item>
               <item>Smalege.</item>
               <item>Saluia.</item>
               <item>Satureia.</item>
               <item>Saxfrage.</item>
               <item>Scabioſa.</item>
               <item>Sothernwood.</item>
               <item>Syngrene.</item>
               <item>Stytcheworte.</item>
               <item>Scamony.</item>
               <item>Sene.</item>
               <item>Selondyne.</item>
               <item>Sauayne.</item>
               <item>Scabioſe.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3925:61"/>¶Towncreſſes.</item>
               <item>Tapſubarbeſto.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>¶Vyolet.</item>
               <item>Vua ſuauis.</item>
               <item>Veruayne.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W</head>
               <item>¶watercreſſes wylde</item>
               <item>Neppe or wodbynde.</item>
               <item>Vvormwoode.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>¶The vertue of the Oken tre.</item>
               <item>¶The Oken lefe.</item>
               <item>¶The makynge of Aqua vite perfectiſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma.</item>
               <item>¶Graffynge and plantynge.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>Finis Tabule.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprynted by me Robert wyer, dwellynge in ſaint Martyns pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe, at the ſygne of ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Euangelyſt, beſyde Charyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge Croſſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3925:61"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
